<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The present state of Denmark and reflections upon the ancient state thereof. Together with a particular account of the birth, education, martial atchievements and brave performances of His Royal Highness Prince George, only brother of His present Majesty of Denmark. / By G. Pierreville Gent. Secretary to the King's Minister at the Court of Denmark.</title>
            <author>Pierreville, Gideon.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 209 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2212A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203183</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077559</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077559</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90698)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2269:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The present state of Denmark and reflections upon the ancient state thereof. Together with a particular account of the birth, education, martial atchievements and brave performances of His Royal Highness Prince George, only brother of His present Majesty of Denmark. / By G. Pierreville Gent. Secretary to the King's Minister at the Court of Denmark.</title>
                  <author>Pierreville, Gideon.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 96, 99-150 p. : port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Benbridg [sic] in Huggins alley in Woodstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Christ Church Library, Oxford, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Denmark --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scandinavia --  Description and travel --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:151645:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <p>His Royall Highneſs Prince GEORGE. Brother to Chriſtian, the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> the Preſent King of Denmarke Etate ſue 30. 1683</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151645:1"/>
            <p>THE Preſent State OF DENMARK, AND REFLECTIONS UPON THE Ancient State thereof.</p>
            <p>Together with a particular Account of the Birth, Education, Martial At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chievements, and brave Performan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Royal Highneſs Prince <hi>GEORGE,</hi> Only Brother to His preſent Majeſty of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>G. Pierreville</hi> Gent. Secretary to the King's Miniſter at the Court of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Benbridg</hi> in <hi>Hug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins</hi> Alley in <hi>Woodſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:151645:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:151645:2"/>
            <head>To His Grace Charles Seamour, Duke of <hi>Somerſet,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving been ſome years Secretary to the King's Miniſter at the Court of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and brought ſome Memoirs from thence relating both to the Ancient and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
<pb facs="tcp:151645:3"/>State of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, I was prevailed with, through the Importunities of ſome Friends, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit them to the Preſs. For the <hi>Northern</hi> Regions not lying in the uſual Road of our Travellers, and not being thought to have any thing ſufficiently inviting as to engage them to undergo the inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and hardſhips that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend all Voyages into thoſe Parts, nor to make ſuch a ſtay as is requiſite for the
<pb facs="tcp:151645:3"/>rendring their Obſervations worthy of the Curioſity of the Age. We are gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally very much in the Dark as to the Government and Manners of thoſe People. This has made me liable, ſince my return from thoſe Climats, to daily Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions about them, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of late, ſince the Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of the Match between my Lady <hi>Ann,</hi> and Prince <hi>George;</hi> People beginning to accuſe themſelves for entertaining ſo ſlender an
<pb facs="tcp:151645:4"/>Opinion of theſe Countries, that can produce a Prince every way ſo great, and endued with ſuch Royal Qualities, as is His Royal Highneſs.</p>
            <p>Though theſe Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions made me give way to the inſtancy of my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, yet I could not reſolve upon the making them publick, without im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploring the Patronage of your Graces Illuſtrious Name. And though I ought to have curb'd my
<pb facs="tcp:151645:4"/>Preſumption from offering you up ſo unpoliſht, and ſo imperfect an Oblation, yet hoping that ſome things in it might merit your Graces Speculation, I flatter'd my ſelf that your Grace a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding with ſo much goodneſs, would pardon in me the Ambition I had to declare the profound Zeal, Reſpect and Submiſſion wherewith I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>Your Graces Moſt humble and moſt obedient Servant, G. PIERREVILLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:151645:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:151645:5"/>
            <head>THE <hi>Preſent State</hi> OF <hi>DENMARK.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining that part of the <hi>Cimbrick, Cherſoneſe,</hi> called <hi>Juitland, Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein,</hi> a great Shoal of Iſlands, the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal whereof are <hi>Zealand, Funen,</hi> and many more, but of leſs Note, with the great continent of <hi>Norway,</hi> and the Iſles thereof, is Bounded on the <hi>Weſt</hi> with the Main <hi>Weſtern</hi> Ocean, on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> with the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick</hi> Sea, on the <hi>North-Eaſt</hi> with part of <hi>Sweedland, Full-North</hi> with the Main Frozen Ocean, and on the <hi>South</hi> with <hi>Germany,</hi> from which it is ſeperated on the <hi>South-weſt</hi> by the River <hi>Albis,</hi> and on the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> by the <hi>Trave,</hi> a ſmall <hi>Iſthmus</hi> or Neck of Land Uniting it to that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent.</p>
            <p>It had its Name from the People of thoſe many Iſlands which lie together in the <hi>Bay</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151645:6"/>or <hi>Gulph,</hi> called <hi>Sinus Codanus,</hi> (Now the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea,) who took upon them the Name of <hi>Danes,</hi> Extending their Name afterwards as they did their Conqueſt, and not from <hi>Dan</hi> a Fabulous King thereof, above a Thouſand years before the Birth of our Saviour.</p>
            <p>As for its Poſition in regard of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens, part of it lieth within the <hi>Northern</hi> temperate <hi>Zone,</hi> and part within the <hi>Artict</hi> Circle; reaching from the middle Parallel of the 10th Clime, or 55 Degree of Latitude, where it Joyneth with <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> as far as the 71 Degree, where the Frozen Ocean is its only Boundary, thus the longeſt Day in the <hi>Southern</hi> parts hereof, is 17 hours and a quarter: But in the parts fartheſt <hi>North,</hi> they have no Night for two whole Months, three Weeks, one day, and ſome Seaven hours over; as on the Contrary, no Day for the like ſpace of time, when the Sun is fartheſt diſtant in the other <hi>Tropick.</hi> Thus the Air would be very ſharp and bitter, were it not Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perated by the warm Vapours of the Sun, by which means in <hi>Juitland, Zealand,</hi> and the Adjoyning Iſlands, it is not ſo Cold as in places which lie much more <hi>South.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now tho the Land be Naturally Sterile, and affording little beſides Woods and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:151645:6"/>Mountains, yet the Care and Induſtry of the Inhabitants have made it very Fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Denmark</hi> abounds in Rich Paſtures, which Feed ſuch vaſt Numbers of Cattle, that it has been ſome times known, that in one Year a Hundred-Thouſand Cows and Oxen, have been hence Exported in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Germany</hi> and the <hi>Netherlands;</hi> which brings a Vaſt Income to the Kingdom, nor do they want excellent Breeds of Horſes, that part of it called <hi>Oldenburg</hi> eſpecially, Furniſhing the beſt and fineſt Coach-Horſes of all <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Sea Coaſts of <hi>Juitland, Zealand,</hi> and other parts of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Territories, are plied with ſuch Vaſt Shoals of <hi>Herrings, Plaiſe, Whitings, Cod,</hi> and other Fiſh, that they are almoſt capable of Hindring the Paſſage of Boats and Ships.</p>
            <p>Nor are their Forreſts leſs ſtocked with Veniſon, there being no leſs every Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Seaſon than Fifteen Hundred <hi>Bucks</hi> brought into the Kings Pallaces, beſides Vaſt numbers of Wilde <hi>Boars, Hares,</hi> and ſuch like ſort of Gaim.</p>
            <p>Notwithſtanding, the mean Opinion which the <hi>Romans</hi> had, and the Ill Charact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er they have given us of all the <hi>Northern</hi> Nations, yet they found themſelves con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151645:7"/>to Buckle under their Vigourous Attacks, and abandon their City and Country as a Prey to the Pillage and Mercy of the Triumphing <hi>Cambrians,</hi> nor are the other <hi>Northern</hi> Nations, inſenſible of the Mettle and keenneſs of the <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh</hi> Swords; the <hi>Danes</hi> having Conquered <hi>Ireland</hi> no leſs than Eight ſeveral times, Beaten, the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ten times and who for a long while were Subject to the Kings of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark; Scotland</hi> for ſome time Tributary to this Crown; <hi>Saxony</hi> has paid Homage to ſeveral of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, and <hi>Sweeden</hi> frequently own'd e'm for their Soveraigns, nor is the Kingdom of <hi>Norway</hi> a ſmall proof of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Courage, neither have their Women been Barren of Brave per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formances, their Exploits being equally Glorious with thoſe of the greateſt Heroes of other Nations. But Valour and War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Conduct are not the only qualities praiſe worthy in the <hi>Danes,</hi> they are no leſs to be Commended for their. Hoſpita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Extraordinary Complaiſance to all Strangers; and tho their Entertainments do ſometimes degenerate into Luxury and exceſs, yet without doubt the Crime is much more Pardonable in them than thoſe who live under a more happy Climate. The <hi>Danes</hi> indeed are Haughty and Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151645:7"/>Jealous of their Honor, revenging the leaſt outrage and contempt, and reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a High Degree all things which give the leaſt apprehenſion of an Affront, and as they are Rigorous Proſecutors of Inſults done to themſelves, ſo are they no leſs ſevere Puniſhers of Criminals of State, eſpecially Thieves and Pirates. And as they are Peremptory in their Executing of Juſtice upon Offenders, ſo are they moſt Religious in doing and Diſtributing it where due, and Inviolable obſervers of their Words and Contracts.</p>
            <p>The Bulck and Stature of the Bodies of the <hi>Danes,</hi> does in ſomewiſe ſuit with the Grandure of their minds, and tho the Luxu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Age has ſo far prevailed in <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> as to quaſh the growth of their Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Danes</hi> in reſpect of their Anceſtors, yet they be ſtill more Large, Strong, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, and long Liv'd than moſt or any of their Neighbours. They are generally fair Complexion'd, their Hair ſomething in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to Yellow.</p>
            <p>Their common Food is on Corn, Fiſh, and all manner of Tame and Wild Beaſts that are Mans Meat, which they have in great abundance. And amongſt their many kind of Fowl, they have greater ſtore of Wood-Cocks than any other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:151645:8"/>whatſoever. The Old Liquor of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> was <hi>Oel,</hi> (<hi>Ale,</hi> or <hi>Beer,</hi>) made of Malt and Water, and is ſtill their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon and moſt general Drink. And tho Wine has now obtain'd much among them, yet perhaps their exceſs therein has Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tailed much of their priſtine Vigour, and that had they kept conſtant and ſolely to their <hi>Oel,</hi> it might have ſpirited them to as great Actions as thoſe of their Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Language, it is only a diſtinct Dialogue of the <hi>Teutonick,</hi> the <hi>High-Dutch, Sweediſh, Norwegion, Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian,</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> being no more, and all Derived from one Mother Tongue.</p>
            <p>As for the Government of <hi>Denmark,</hi> without dwelling upon the Fabulous ſtories of King <hi>Dan,</hi> it is Evidently to be made out, that it was a Monarchy in the Conſultſhip of <hi>Catulus</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> near a hundred years before <hi>Chriſt,</hi> after which we have an account of one <hi>Gothrick</hi> King of the <hi>Danes</hi> in the time of the Emperour <hi>Charles Magne,</hi> from whom the preſent King of <hi>Denmark</hi> is Deſcended in a Lineal Succeſſion, though ſome Authors do affirm that the Ancient Line failed in the Death of King <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> the 3d.</p>
            <p>The Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> it ſelf was
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151645:8"/>Elective untill the year 1660. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs the <hi>Senatours</hi> generally choſe the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Son of their Soveraign, who from that time forth was Stiled the Prince, and the other of the Kings Sons, the Dukes and Heirs of <hi>Norway.</hi> Now their Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in former times was performed after a very Solemn manner, for as many of the Nobles as were <hi>Senatours,</hi> and had Power of Voting and giving their ſuffrages, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pitcht upon ſome Commodious place in the Fields, where having placed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Circle, upon ſo many great Stones they paſt their Votes, and having Seated their new Elected Soveraign in the middle, upon a Stone Higher than the Reſt, they Saluted Him King. There being to this Day in <hi>Zealand</hi> ſuch a company of Stones which bear the Name of <hi>King-Seat.</hi> But after the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> had been thus Elective for above Two Hundred years in the preſent <hi>Oldenburg</hi> Family, the chief Power of Election, as I ſaid being, in the Nobility, thoſe Nobles took this means and occaſion to Capitulate advantages to themſelves, as Previous and Preliminary Conditions to the Election, which every ſucceeding King was forced to comply with, to the Curtailing, Diſpoiling, and Weakning of the Crown, and to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:151645:9"/>and diſadvantage of the other Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Kingdom, inſomuch that none but a Noble Man could Buy, Purchaſe, or poſſeſs in his own Right any Seigniory or Mannour. A Cittizen or Burgher was not capable of purchaſing more than a Houſe, and perhaps a Guarden and an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chard, or ſome ſuch ſlender buſineſs. The Lands and Revenues of the Crown were let our to Noble Men, it may be not to the Third, often not to the Fourth part of what they were really worth, and yet the King could not raiſe the Old Rents, tho the Nobles in the mean while kept the under-tennents Chewing upon a rack Rent. The Peſants in the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Iſland were Villains Reguardant to the Mannors of Noble Men. All publick Offices and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancements were Monopolized by the Nobility. And meer merit without the Circumſtances of Nobility of Extraction and Grandure of State, was excluded all Countenance, Protection and Preferment. Thus the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> which ſhown with ſo much Luſtre, Renown and Glory in former Ages, was Dwindled almoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to an <hi>Ariſtocraſie,</hi> and hardly the ſhaddow of what it had been ſome Centuries before. But upon the Occaſion of a Warr between <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweeden,</hi> and
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:151645:9"/>
               <hi>Frederick</hi> the 3d. King of <hi>Denmark</hi> in the Year 1660. Great Priviledges were pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed and conferred upon the Burgers of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> the better to Encourage them to ſtand the more Valiantly in Defence of their King and Countrey, leaſt the Proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect of mending their Circumſtances un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a new Maſter, ſhould prevail with them to abandon their Old. Now the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges Eſtabliſhed in that juncture were an equal admiſſion to Offices and Honours, according to the Deſerts and Capacities of them and their Children, a Power of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſing Lands and Lordſhips with the ſame Rights as the Nobles. <hi>Copenhagen</hi> to be one of the Eſtates of the Kingdom, and to have a Suffrage in all publick Councels and Reſolves, and the Crown turn'd from Elective to Hereditary, and ſo freed from the Guardianſhip of the Nobility. Thus that juncture, how Menacing ſoever it ſeemed to the whole Realm of <hi>Denmark,</hi> yet proved of ſuch advantage as to rein-ſtate the King in all that Power that was neceſſary for the Defending of His Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions againſt the Invaſions and Inſults of Forreigners, and the Oppreſſions and Uſurpations of one fellow Subject upon an other. Thus the Complexion of that Government is much more Vigorous, and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:151645:10"/>there is a better Circulation of the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings to be Enjoyed under a happy Sway, ſince this Reformation, than had been for ſome Ages before under ſeveral Reigns together.</p>
            <p>The account of the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> before the Planting of Chriſtianity in that Country, will be found a difficult matter to be Stated, their Chronicles before that time being for the moſt part feign'd and fabulous, as well as that of other Nations. But according to the moſt careful, Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and Modeſteſt Relations of that matter, we ſhall ſet down the following Catalogue.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Harald</hi> being forced to Fly his Kingdom by the Accomplices of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Reinferd,</hi> had recourſe to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Ludowick</hi> for Succour, who Furniſhed him with Forces for the Reinſtating him in his Kingdom, but upon Condition he would abandon his Heatheniſme, and be Converted to Chriſtianity. Accordingly he was Baptized in the year 826, and was forthwith ſet again upon his Throne. But not long after he turn'd Idolater a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, adn ſo remained till he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to Renounce it by St. <hi>Angchar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eric</hi> Succeeded his Brother <hi>Harald,</hi> and though he had been Baptized with
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:151645:10"/>him at the Emperours Court, yet he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted the Chriſtians with the ſame Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty as his Brother had done in the time of his Relapſe. During his Reign, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, about the year 853. the <hi>Danes</hi> are ſaid to have firſt Invaded <hi>France,</hi> under the Conduct of their General <hi>Rollo,</hi> though others would have <hi>Gotfrid</hi> to have made the firſt Eruption into that Kingdom, and that <hi>Rollo</hi> did not enter <hi>France</hi> till the year 876. and was not Eſtabliſhed peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably in <hi>Normandy,</hi> till 889. or 890.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Eric Barn,</hi> or the Child being the only Male left alive of the Royal Family after the Bloody Wars between <hi>Eric</hi> and <hi>Guthorn</hi> King of <hi>Norway.</hi> But he had not been long upon the Throne, before he Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed the Perſecution upon the Chriſtians with more Cruelty then his Prodeceſſors had done, deſtroying more Churches, Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and Religious Houſes, then all the other <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings put together; He Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted his Wars in <hi>Germany</hi> with great Gallantry and Conduct, Slaying with his own Hands <hi>Bruno</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony,</hi> and Twelve Counts. He Departed this Life in the year 902.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Canutus Lodneknut</hi> or the <hi>Hairy</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his Father <hi>Eric.</hi> In his time every Third Man in <hi>Denmark</hi> went to ſeek his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:151645:11"/>Fortune, and thoſe who went away thus upon theſe Expeditions over-run all <hi>Pruſia, Courland, Semgal,</hi> and other Countries, where they Eſtabliſhed themſelves, and where their Poſterity remain unto this day, He Dyed a <hi>Pagan</hi> in the year 912. And was Succeeded by</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Frotho</hi> his Son, though ſome ſay <hi>Sueno</hi> his Brother Reigned Nine years. He was twenty years King of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> being Converted to Chriſtianity in <hi>England,</hi> and Dyed a zealous Chriſtian, his next Succeſſors was,</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Gormo, Gormund,</hi> or <hi>Guthram</hi> (Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naned <hi>Harteſnute,</hi> and <hi>Engelander,</hi> becauſe Born in <hi>England:</hi> He with his Attendants was Baptized at <hi>Aal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e</hi> in <hi>Somerſetſhire,</hi> our Learned and Pious King <hi>Alfred</hi> being his Godfather, and gave him the Name of <hi>Athelſtanes,</hi> and the Kingdom of the <hi>Eaſt-Angles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. <hi>Harald</hi> Surnamed <hi>Blaat and</hi> Succeed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Father <hi>Gormo.</hi> In his days did the <hi>Danes</hi> make that Famous Trench between <hi>Gottorp</hi> and <hi>Sleſwick</hi> called <hi>Dannewerk.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Sueno</hi> or <hi>Suenotho,</hi> Surnamed <hi>Tuiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keg</hi> (that is <hi>Fork'd Beard,</hi>) Succeeded <hi>Harald.</hi> At his firſt coming to the Crown he was a <hi>Pagan,</hi> and Exerciſed great Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty upon the Chriſtians, but was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:151645:11"/>Converted to Chriſtianity, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected three Biſhopricks at <hi>Sleſwick, Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,</hi> and <hi>Arhuſen.</hi> He is by ſome ſaid to have Dyed in the year 1012. and was Buryed at <hi>York,</hi> Others in 1014. and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tombed in <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Canutus</hi> the Great, (Son to <hi>Sueno</hi>) He was at once King of <hi>England, Denmark, Sweeden, Norway, Slavonia,</hi> and <hi>Sambland,</hi> ſome ſay too, King or Duke of <hi>Normandy.</hi> He was Buryed at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> in the year 1036. after he had been Seaven and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> twenty four of <hi>England,</hi> and Seaven of <hi>Norway,</hi> and was Suoceeded in the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> by his Son.</p>
            <p n="10">10. <hi>Hardi-Cnute,</hi> who within four years obtained the Kingdom of <hi>England</hi> upon the Death of his Brother <hi>Harald.</hi> He Dyed in <hi>England</hi> in the year 1041. and was Buryed by his Father in the Cathedral of <hi>Wincheſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">11. <hi>Magnus,</hi> King of <hi>Norway,</hi> poſſeſſed himſelf of the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> by main force upon the Death of <hi>Hardi-Cnute,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending a Contract that Entituled him to it, but had it not long in poſſeſſion. He Dyed in the year 1048. and left the Crown to</p>
            <p n="12">12. <hi>Sueno Eſthret,</hi> Son of one <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lf</hi> an
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:151645:12"/>
               <hi>Engliſh</hi> Earl. He Departed this Life in the year 1074. and left behind him five Sons, who all of them Enjoyed Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively their Fathers Crown.</p>
            <p n="13">13. <hi>Harald Sueno</hi>'s Eldeſt Son, Swayed the Scepter no longer then two years, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an eaſie efferninate, timerous Prince. So that the <hi>Engliſh</hi> laid hold of the Juncture, ſhook off the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Yoak without any great trouble.</p>
            <p n="14">14. St. <hi>Canutus,</hi> the Second Son of King <hi>Swain</hi> in the year 1088. was Inhumanly Murdered by his own Subject at St. <hi>Albans</hi> Church in <hi>Odenſee</hi> (a City in the Iſle of <hi>Funen</hi>) which he had made his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. Now his Brother <hi>Olaf</hi> longing for the Crown, Fomented a Rebellion againſt <hi>Canutus,</hi> and effected his deſigns, by the means of the Kings commanding his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to pay Tyths, according to the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtom of other Nations. And this Foment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the People into ſuch a Rage by <hi>Olafs</hi> practiſes, that nothing could appeaſe but their Soveraigns Martyrdome.</p>
            <p n="15">15. <hi>Olaf</hi> the Third Son of <hi>Swain</hi> upon the Aſſaſſination of St. <hi>Canutus,</hi> was Unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouſly Declared King by his Partizans. But he and the whole Kingdom were not long before they received their juſt Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment for that Execrable Crime of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:151645:12"/>Murdering their Prince, for Heaven was pleas'd to ſend ſo great a Famine over all <hi>Denmark,</hi> that the Kings own Family wanted Bread. <hi>Olaf</hi> well knowing his Crimes had brought that Judgment upon the Realm, offered up his Prayers to God that he would be pleaſed to divert the Stream of his Vengeance from off the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, upon his Head that had offended; Whereupon the very ſame Night he Dyed Hungry and Wretched in the year 1096, and the Famine forthwith abated.</p>
            <p n="16">16. <hi>Eric Swains</hi> Fourth Son, Surnamed the <hi>Good,</hi> for his Religious Zeal and Piety, Dyed in his Pilgrimage towards <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and was Buried in the Iſle of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> in the year 1106. during his Reign <hi>Lunden</hi> in <hi>Schonen</hi> was made an Arch-Biſhops See, all the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Biſhops being before that time under the Juriſdiction of the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Brement.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">17. <hi>Nicholas Suenos</hi>'s youngeſt Son Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded his Brother, but was Slain in the year 1135. by the <hi>Jutes</hi> in Revenge of the Death of <hi>Chute</hi> Duke of <hi>Flanders,</hi> whom he had cauſed to be Aſſaſſinated in the Church.</p>
            <p n="18">18. <hi>Eric Emund</hi> a good Religious Prince, Succeeded his Uncle <hi>Nicarlus;</hi> &amp; in the year 1130. was in his own Pallace Inhumanly
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:151645:13"/>Aſſaſſinated by one <hi>Plagſorte</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Juitland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="19">19. <hi>Eric Lamb</hi> Succeeded his Unckle <hi>Eric Emund.</hi> But after a while laid down his Crown, and retired into a Monaſtry at <hi>Odenſce</hi> in <hi>Funen,</hi> where he departed this Life, in the year 1147.</p>
            <p n="20">20. <hi>Swain Gratenhede, Eric Emunds</hi> Son got the Crown upon the Death of his Kinſman <hi>Eric. Lamb.</hi> Three Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> were at the ſame time in this Princes days. One part of the People be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Cnute,</hi> King <hi>Nicholas</hi>'s Grand-Child, another for <hi>Waldemar,</hi> Son to <hi>Cnute</hi> Duke of <hi>Flanders.</hi> After ſome Ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counters and Combates wherein both <hi>Swain</hi> and <hi>Cnute</hi> were Killed, the whole Realm was Swayed by</p>
            <p n="21">21. <hi>Waldemar</hi> Surnamed the Great, who was Soveraign of all the Countries on the <hi>North</hi> of the <hi>Elb,</hi> and Departed this Life in the year 1182. Leaving the Crown to his Son.</p>
            <p n="22">22. <hi>Cnutes</hi> who ſhewed great Conduct and Gallantry in his Wars with the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Emperour, who demanded Homage of the Kings of <hi>Denmark.</hi> He Dyed at <hi>Ringſted</hi> in the year 1202.</p>
            <p n="23">23. <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Second, Succeeded his Brother. He new Modelled the <hi>Daniſh</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:151645:13"/>Government, Subdued <hi>Norway,</hi> overcame and put to Flight the Emperour <hi>Otto,</hi> who meant to render himſelf Maſter of <hi>Holſtein;</hi> and having Sway'd the Scepter Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly for Thirty Nine Years, he Dyed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1241. and was Succeeded by</p>
            <p n="24">24. <hi>Eric Plog-penning</hi> his Son, who was taken at <hi>Sleſwick</hi> and Slain by his Brother</p>
            <p n="25">25. <hi>Abel,</hi> who having Reigned two years after a Wicked manner, was then Aſſaſſinated by Rebels in the year 1252. and was Succeeded by his Brother</p>
            <p n="26">26. <hi>Chriſtophers,</hi> who having Lived in a continual War with his own Rebellious Subjects, is ſaid to have been Poyſoned in the year 1259. by <hi>Arnefaſt</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Arhuſen,</hi> as the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth was afterwards by <hi>Bernardine</hi> the <hi>Monk</hi> with the <hi>Euchariſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="27">27. <hi>Eric Glipping,</hi> (the Son of King <hi>Chriſtopher</hi>) being poſſeſſed of his Fathers Scepter, Lived one of the moſt Leudeſt and Debaucheſt Lives Imaginable, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting all manner of Sacriledges, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Oppreſſions, and Whoredoms, till he was Aſſaſſinated with Fifty ſix (ſome ſay Seventy,) Wounds, as he was Sleeping one Night in a Barn at <hi>Findetorp;</hi> a ſmall Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Wiberg,</hi> by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:151645:14"/>Ruffians hired to Kill him, by <hi>Andrew Soiget</hi> Marſhal of <hi>Denmark,</hi> whoſe Wife he had Raviſhed, and ſome others of the Nobility in the year 1286. and was Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by</p>
            <p n="28">28. <hi>Eric Menved, Glippings</hi> Son, who was as good and Pious a Prince, as his Father was Impious and Wicked, being preſerved by Providence, from the Death and Murder which was Plotted by the Conſpiraters againſt his Fathers Life. He Dyed peaceably as he had Lived, in the year 1319. was Buryed at <hi>Ringſtad,</hi> and Succeeded by his Brother</p>
            <p n="29">29. <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> the Second, much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like his Predeceſſor, being a Cruel, Perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious, Unfortunate, and Sloathful Prince, a Hater of all, and Hated by all. Having lingred out a Reign of Thirteen years, in 1333, he Dyed at <hi>Niccoping</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Falſter,</hi> being forſaken of all, neglected and unpittyed. After this Princes Death, there was an <hi>Inter-regnum</hi> of fifteen years, but the <hi>Danes</hi> growing Senſible of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſions they lay under for want of a Head, reſolved to Settle</p>
            <p n="30">30. <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Third King, King <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtophers</hi> Son upon the Throne of his Father. He pull'd down the Uſurpers, and Recollect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſcatter'd Members of the Realm,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:151645:14"/>without much Moleſtation. He is ſaid to have been a Prince endued with all thoſe Great Qualities that can adorn a Throne. When Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> the 11th threatned to Excommunicate him for his ſaucy Behaviour, in the Stile of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> he returned this Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Waldemar <hi>King of</hi> Denmark, &amp;c. <hi>To the Biſhop of</hi> Rome, <hi>Sendeth Greeting. We hold our Life from God, our Kingdom from our Subjects, our Riches from our Parents, and our Faith from thy Predeceſſor, which if thou wilt not Grant us any longer, We do by theſe Preſents Reſigne, Farewell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He Dyed in the year 1378. and was Buryed by his Father at <hi>Sora,</hi> and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded by his Daughter</p>
            <p n="31">31. <hi>Margaret,</hi> who was Crowned Queen of <hi>Denmark</hi> upon the Death of her Father, and Sway'd the Scepter with more Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Conduct than any of her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, ſhe taking in one Campaign <hi>Albert</hi> King of <hi>Sweeden, Rodulph</hi> Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Scharen,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Mecklen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Holſtein</hi> and <hi>Reppin</hi> Priſoners. ſhe Dyed a great Friend to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion and Patroneſs to the Clergy, and was Buryed at <hi>Roſchild</hi> in the year 1412. Her Father was uſed to ſay, <hi>That Nature
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:151645:15"/>intended her for a Man, but Spoiled her in the making.</hi> She left the Crown to</p>
            <p n="32">32. <hi>Eric,</hi> the Son of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ratiſlaw</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Duke of <hi>Pomeren,</hi> her Great Nephew who having Reigned many years like a cruel Tyrant, was at length conſtrained to abandon his Throne, and Fly from the Fury of his Incens'd Nobility into <hi>Gothland,</hi> taking with him a vaſt Treaſure, and one <hi>Cicilia</hi> his Miſs, who by the Influence ſhe had over him, brought him to that wretched condition.</p>
            <p n="33">33. <hi>Chriſtopher,</hi> Duke of <hi>Bavaria</hi> and Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> another of King <hi>Waldemars</hi> great Grand Children, ſucceeding <hi>Eric</hi> in the Kingdoms of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, Norway</hi> and <hi>Sweeden,</hi> His ſway was ſhort, but Glorious and ſucceſsful, more eſpecially proſperous in his Warrs againſt the Rebells in <hi>Juitland,</hi> and the <hi>Hans-Towns.</hi> He died without Iſſue at <hi>Helſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> in the year 1447.</p>
            <p n="34">34. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> 1. <hi>Theodoric</hi> Count of <hi>Ol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburgs</hi> Son, was choſen King of <hi>Denmark</hi> upon the Death of King <hi>Chriſtopher;</hi> he had all the Royal Quallities that can Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate a Throne; He reduced the <hi>Sweeds</hi> to their Allegiance, who had Revolted from the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of His Reign, added <hi>Holſtein</hi> to His
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:151645:15"/>Dominions, made Himſelf Duke of <hi>Dith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mars</hi> and <hi>Stormar,</hi> and having ſwayed the Scepter Three and Thirty years; He Died in Peace in the year 1481. and was Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried a in Chappel of his own Building at <hi>Roſchild,</hi> leaving his Scepture to</p>
            <p n="35">35. <hi>John</hi> his Son, who was a Generous, Valiant and Pious Prince, and very proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous in almoſt all His undertakings. He Died of the Plague at <hi>Olburg,</hi> in the year 1513.</p>
            <p n="36">36. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the 2d. his Son ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Him, who was the greateſt Tyrant, not only that ever ſwayed the Scepter of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> but perhaps that ever any other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did produce. He is ſaid (to have been Born with one Hand graſp'd, which when the Midwife open'd, ſhe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> found full of Blood. Thus, when by the Barbarity and Cruelty of his Reign, He had been compelled to abandon the poſſeſſion of Three Kingdoms, and had underwent the Miſeries of Baniſhment and Impriſonment for ſix and Thirty years, He Died wretch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly in the Caſtle of <hi>Kallenburg</hi> in <hi>Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> in the year 1559. and was ſucceeded by his Uncle</p>
            <p n="37">37. <hi>Federic</hi> the 1. King <hi>John</hi>'s Brother, Immediately after his Coronation, He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to Introduce the <hi>Augsburg</hi> Confeſſion
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:151645:16"/>into all the Churches of <hi>Denmark,</hi> He ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Septer almoſt Ten years in Peace and quietneſs, and Died at <hi>Sleſwig</hi> in the year 1533.</p>
            <p n="38">38. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Third <hi>Fredericks</hi> Son, Succeeded his Father. He compleated the Reformation which his Father had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in the Church, is celebrated for all the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> and Royal Vertues that a Prince can ſtand poſſeſſed off; His Reign having been exceeding Happy, both to himſelf and his Subjects, he left the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to his Son.</p>
            <p n="39">39. <hi>Frederick</hi> the II. who was a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Obſerver of the Steps of his Father, and after a proſperous Reign of Nine and Twenty Years, Died in his Pallace at <hi>Anderſcow</hi> in the year 1587. and had for his Succeſſor</p>
            <p n="40">40. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the IV. who before his Fathers Burial was choſen, and ſoon after Crowned King of <hi>Denmark;</hi> During his Reign <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the II. Emperour of <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> over-run the greateſt part of the <hi>Cimbrian Cherſoneſe,</hi> and had almoſt Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued the whole Kingdom of <hi>Denmark;</hi> but King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> uſing his laſt efforts, conſtrained the Imperaliſts to retire, and made an Honourable Peace, he Died in the year 1648. and was Succeeded by</p>
            <p n="41">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:151645:16"/>
41. <hi>Frederick</hi> the Third his Son; About the middle of this Princes Reign, his Crown had like to have been taken of his Head by the Victorious <hi>Charles Guſtave</hi> King of <hi>Sweeden,</hi> who had reduced him to that Extremity, as that he had nothing more left then his Town of <hi>Copenhaguen,</hi> but the Emperonr, King of <hi>Poland,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Nothern</hi> Princes, confederating toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the King of <hi>Sweeden</hi> was compelled to the Treaty at <hi>Roſchild,</hi> which neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs ſtripped <hi>Denmark</hi> of many of it's beſt holds and Provinces; Yet the Crown re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this advantage as to be made He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riditary in the preſent Family, and the People, inſtead of many Tyrants which they had in the Nobles no more one Maſter. He Dyed of a Feaver the twenty fifth day of <hi>February</hi> 1669. and that Night the Nobility Swore Allegiance to the New King.</p>
            <p n="42">42. <hi>Chrſtian</hi> Fifth now Reigning Anactive and Valiant Prince, was Born on the 18th of <hi>April</hi> 1646. Elected King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and acknowledged Heir of that Crown on the 12 of <hi>June</hi> 1650, Married on the 10 of <hi>May</hi> 1667 <hi>Charlotta, Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe Caſtle,</hi> the Daughter of the <hi>Landgrave William,</hi> and of <hi>Hedwige, Sophina</hi> Electoral Princeſs of <hi>Brandenburg,</hi> the Ceremony of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:151645:17"/>their Marriage was performed at <hi>Niccoping</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Falſter,</hi> in the Month of <hi>July</hi> in the ſame year, with all the Splendour and magnificence Imaginable; by this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, the King has a numerous Iſſue. But before I proceed to give an Account of the Royal Family, it is convenient I firſt ſet down, ſome Circumſtances relating to the preſent King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Perſon, his Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Arms, Dominions, Patrimony, Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue, and Strength, his Power, Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, Supremacy, Soveraignty, and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. And then I ſhall proceed to the giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Account of the Nobility and Orders of the Knight-hood of that Kingdome, with ſeveral other particulars, ending with a Geographical, or rather Topographical, Deſcriptions of the ſeveral Provinces and Places belonging to that Crown. And now firſt, as to his Perſon, having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy mentioned his Birth, Marriage, and Coronation; Than that he is poſſeſſed of all the advantages which Nature or Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation could afford, which have been ſo well Seconded by Fortune in ſeveral Expeditions into <hi>Schonen</hi> and <hi>Germany,</hi> and the engagements of his Fleets, that he is become the Darling of his People, and the Terror and Admiration of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:151645:17"/>
The King of <hi>Denmarks</hi> Title now is King of <hi>Denmark, Norway,</hi> of the <hi>Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandales;</hi> Duke of <hi>Sleſwick, Holſtein, Stormar,</hi> and <hi>Ditmarſh;</hi> Count of <hi>Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh</hi> and <hi>Delmenhorſt.</hi> It was much more pompous formerly, when he Swel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out the Catalogue of his Dominions, with <hi>England, Sweeden,</hi> and other Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
            <p>The Ancient <hi>Cimbrians</hi> are ſaid to have had their Shields and Helmets Painted with the Shapes of ſeveral ſorts of Wild Beaſts, and ſometimes uſed to ſet a Bra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen-Bull upon the top of their Standard, as a token of Strength and Valour. But at this time the King of <hi>Denmark's</hi> Coat is a Complication of Fourteen ſeveral Coats, thus ordered.</p>
            <p>In a Field <hi>Gules,</hi> He bears a Croſs <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent</hi> (the Arms of the Houſe of <hi>Oldenburgh</hi>) which quarters the upper part of the Coat into four Cantons; The Firſt of theſe gives (the Arms of <hi>Denmark,</hi>) <hi>Or,</hi> Six half Hearts <hi>Gules,</hi> three <hi>Lyons Paſſant,</hi> Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant <hi>Azure,</hi> with Crowns of the Firſt. This Coat is parted with (the Arms of <hi>Norway</hi>) <hi>Gules,</hi> a Lyon Crowned <hi>Or,</hi> holding in his paws an Hatchet <hi>Argent,</hi> with an haft of the Second. The Second <hi>Canton</hi> carries <hi>Gules,</hi> a <hi>Leopard</hi> in Chief
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:151645:18"/>
               <hi>Or,</hi> the Field Sown with nine Hearts of the Second, which are the Arms of <hi>Gothland;</hi> theſe are parted with <hi>Gules,</hi> a <hi>Dragon</hi> Crowned <hi>Or,</hi> the Ancient Coat of the <hi>Vandals</hi> or <hi>Slavonians;</hi> the Third <hi>Canton</hi> gives <hi>Azure,</hi> Three Crowns <hi>Or,</hi> to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>note the Union of the Three Kingdoms of <hi>Denmark, Norway,</hi> and <hi>Sweeden.</hi> This Coat is parted with <hi>Gules,</hi> a <hi>Paſchal-Lamb Argent,</hi> holding a Croſs <hi>Or,</hi> at which hangs a Streamer of the Second, charged with a ſmall Croſs of the Firſt. The firſt Original of this Coat, is ſaid to have been this, In the Year 1218. when King <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Second Engaged in a Sharp and Bloody War with the <hi>Lifelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Troops having loſt their Standard, began to be disheartned to that Degree, that they gave Ground, and were ready to fling down their Arms, out of diſpair, and yield the Victory to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens. When a new Standard of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain fell from Heaven, Diſplaying a White Croſs in a Bloody-Flag; At the ſight whereof the <hi>Danes</hi> forthwith Ral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyed their Forces that were Diſperſed, with that Vigour and Courage, as ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered them in a ſhort time Maſters of the Field. The Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> kept the Holy Flag in Remembrance of ſo Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:151645:18"/>a Deliverance, with all the care and Veneration imaginable; Believing their Future Succeſs did in a high Degree depend upon the Safety of ſo Sacred a Banner. But though the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Hiſtorians do Aſſert this to be the ſource of this part of the Arms of their Kings, yet it is much more reaſonable to believe that this Banner was beſtowed by the Pope upon their King, when he undertook that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedition into <hi>Lifeland,</hi> ſince the main De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of that War was the Converſion of thoſe Infidels. But to proceed, the Fourth Canton, bears <hi>Or,</hi> two <hi>Lyons Paſſant A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zure,</hi> which are the Arms of <hi>Sleſwic,</hi> theſe are parted with <hi>Gules,</hi> an headleſs Fiſh, ſtuck on a Stake, and Crown'd <hi>Argent:</hi> which is the Coat of <hi>Iſeland.</hi> In the Center of theſe four Cantons, and the middle of the great Croſs hangs a Scutcheon bearing <hi>Azure,</hi> a Horſe-Man in compleat Armour <hi>Argent,</hi> holding a Sword in his Right-Hand of the ſame, with the Hilt <hi>Or,</hi> his Horſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with a Cloath of the Second; which are the Arms of <hi>Dithmarſe:</hi> The lower part of the Arms contains four Coats more; Whereof the Firſt is <hi>Gules,</hi> three Pinks, (ſome call them Nails of our Saviours Paſſion) and three Leaves of Nettles, which are intermixed, and meet in Angles
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:151645:19"/>at the Heart of the Coat; which is charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a ſmall Scutcheon <hi>Argent,</hi> for <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein.</hi> The Second (which is the Coat of <hi>Stormaria</hi>) is <hi>Axure,</hi> a <hi>Swan Argent,</hi> with a Coronet round her Neck <hi>Or.</hi> The Third (belonging to the County of <hi>Del<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menhorſt</hi>) is <hi>Or,</hi> two Bars <hi>Gules.</hi> The Fourth and laſt Coat (which belongs to <hi>Jutland</hi>) is <hi>Azure,</hi> a Croſs Patty, at the bottom of it Achet <hi>Or,</hi> below the Arms is uſually hung in a Chain <hi>Or,</hi> the Scutche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the Order of the <hi>Elephant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Helmet <hi>Or,</hi> Embroidered and Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>masked, the ſights covered and wanting Bars; above with a Crown <hi>Or,</hi> encircled with four Circles, and Adorned with pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Stones: On the top of this a Globe <hi>Or,</hi> and above all a Croſs Patty <hi>Argent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Creſt</hi> is a <hi>Leopard,</hi> Paſſant over the Crown <hi>Or,</hi> eight Streamers <hi>Azure,</hi> a plain Croſs <hi>Argent;</hi> four Spears bending to the Dexter ſide, and as many to the Siniſter <hi>Or.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Supported by two <hi>Savages,</hi> Crowned and girt with Ivy <hi>Proper,</hi> Armed with two pointed Clubs.</p>
            <p>The Mantle <hi>Or,</hi> Sown, with Hearts <hi>Gules</hi> and Lions <hi>Azure,</hi> doubled Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine.</p>
            <p>The Ancient Dominions of the King of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:151645:19"/>
               <hi>Denmark,</hi> were of a much Vaſter extent than they are at this day, that Crown poſſeſſing in the time of <hi>Canutus</hi> the Great, <hi>England, Denmark, Sweeden, Norway, Slavonia, Sambland,</hi> and <hi>Normandy,</hi> with ſeveral Iſlands: Whereas now his ſwayreach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es only over <hi>Juitland, Holſtein Zealand, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, Iſeland, Freezland, Greenland,</hi> the <hi>Feroe</hi> and ſome other Iſlands of ſmall Note, with the Counties of <hi>Oldenburg, Stormaria,</hi> and <hi>Dithmarſh,</hi> and alterna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively <hi>Slezwick,</hi> as ſhall be ſhown more at large hereafter, beſides ſome Fortreſſes and Colonies, in the <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt-Indies,</hi> and upon the Coaſt of <hi>Africa.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> have certain Lands Annexed to the Crown, which are inalienable, and in caſe upon the Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities of ſome Junctures, any of them be alienated for the Publick Weale, yet the ſame Prince, or any of his ſucceſſours may reunite them again let the conſideration be what it will of their Alienation.</p>
            <p>But it is no eaſie matter to State the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the yearly Revenue of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> which ariſes from the Rents of Crown Lands, Cuſtomes, and Cuſtome Money, Tiths, and other Contingencies ſome gueſſe may be made of it from the Cuſtomes which are paid by the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant-Ships
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:151645:20"/>which paſs the Sound every day. Every Ship that paſſes by <hi>Elſeneur</hi> muſt pay a <hi>Roſe-Noble</hi> or Four <hi>Rix-Dollars</hi> for every Maſt. And it has been obſerved, that commonly Two hundred Ships, often Four hundred, nay Six hundred paſs in one day. Now allowing only 200 to paſs dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and each pay two <hi>Roſe Nobles</hi> or eight <hi>Rix-Dollars</hi> for two Maſts, the Sum will Amount to about Four hundred Pounds of our Money, for every day in the year round, and for the whole year to about 134400 Pounds. And the Tax which is paid for ſuch Cattel as are Exported, does not fall much ſhort of this; the Cuſtomers Exacting a <hi>Rix-Dollar</hi> for every Beaſt that goes out of their Kings Dominions.</p>
            <p>The chief ſtrength of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> conſiſts in the Number and goodneſs of his Ships and Seamen. And indeed the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Mariners may vye with the beſt of Europe, which formerly Rendred them not only particularly ſuccesful by Sea, but alſo in their Engagements with the <hi>Sweeds</hi> in the laſt Wars. The Naval Forces of the Crown of <hi>Denmark,</hi> were even for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly ſo conſiderable; as that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Second fitted out a hundred good Men of War for the Succour of <hi>Henry</hi> the Second, the <hi>French</hi> King againſt the <hi>Engliſh:</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:151645:20"/>Nevertheleſs this preſent King has a much larger Fleet of his own alwaies ready for Action. And here I cannot forbear taking Notice of the Bravery and Vigour of our Nation, that was able to carry on a War with Glory, and Fight with ſucceſs three ſuch Powers confederated together as his moſt <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Majeſty, the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and the States General of the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Provinces, nay in ſo Mortifying a Conjuncture, as when the Burning of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and the Deſolation of the Plague would have enervated any other than <hi>Engliſh</hi> Courages, diſconcerted their meaſures, and conſtrain'd 'em to have complyed with diſhonourable Terms. But to return; I will here inſert a Liſt of ſuch Men of War of the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> as I could get the Liſt off.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell role="label"> </cell>
                     <cell role="label">Guns.</cell>
                     <cell role="label">Men.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Sophia Amalia.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>106.</cell>
                     <cell>650.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prince Chriſtian.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>80.</cell>
                     <cell>600.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Droning Charlotte.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prince Charlotte.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Prince George.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>80.</cell>
                     <cell>550.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Fur. Prince.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>80.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Princeſs Amalies.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Three Crowns.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>80.</cell>
                     <cell>500.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Northern Lion.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>400.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:151645:21"/>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Three Foldigherds.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>450.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Swan.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>60.</cell>
                     <cell>450.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Three Lions.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>70.</cell>
                     <cell>400.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Victory.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54.</cell>
                     <cell>350.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Lindworm.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>48.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Nettle Leave.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Oldenburg.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>48.</cell>
                     <cell>250.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Spen.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Black Horſeman.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>50.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Guldenlieu.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hope.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>48.</cell>
                     <cell>250.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Delmenhorſt.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>44.</cell>
                     <cell>250.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Copenhagen.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>250.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Black Bear.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                     <cell>200.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Feroe.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>40.</cell>
                     <cell>200.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Chriſtianus Quartus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Frederick.</hi> 3 <abbr>d.</abbr>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>54.</cell>
                     <cell>300.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Venus.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                     <cell>200.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Lobſter.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>36.</cell>
                     <cell>200.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Goldenfiſh.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Virgin.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>28.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Wildman.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>18.</cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Flyin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Hart.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Lubeck.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell> </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>The Hunter.</hi>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>20.</cell>
                     <cell>100.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>With many others, whereof I cannot at preſent call to mind the Names. The <hi>Daniſh</hi> Men of War now are Built much fitter for Service than they were formerly, being neither ſo Large, ſo Bulky, nor ſo
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:151645:21"/>unweildy as they were in the foregoing Ages, but readier either to Attack, Fly, or Purſue. No Prince in Chriſtendom is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Furniſhed with all things neceſſary for the fitting out a Fleet, <hi>Norway</hi> and his other Territories; affording him all the Equipage requiſite for that purpoſe. He is alſo pretty well ſtored with Sea-men, and indeed all his Dominions being Iſlands, or Maritime Provinces, the Inhabitants are almoſt Naturally Mariners. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs this Monarch is ſometimes forced to have recourſe to ſtrangers for Recruits of Men; the <hi>Northern</hi> Countreys not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounding ſo in People as they did in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer times, when they Spawn'd and pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forth ſuch ſhoales as over ran not only moſt parts of <hi>Europe,</hi> but continued their Incurſions into <hi>Aſia;</hi> But whether this be imputed to the Aboliſhing of Poligamy, which the Introducing Chriſtianity did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form, or that the prevailing of Luxury has debilitated their priſtine Vigour, and ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred them the leſs fit for generation, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it is, that no parts of <hi>Europe</hi> are now ſo thin of Inhabitants, as theſe <hi>Northern</hi> Regions, and that the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> has not People enough to Man out ſo many Ships He would be otherwiſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable to fit out: For without Exhauſting
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:151645:22"/>or Impoveriſhing his Coffers, He is able to Build Twelve Men of War every year. And conſidering the Scarcity of Men, His Land Forces are much more conſiderable and better Martialized than they have been under ſome of His lateſt Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors. But before I proceed to particula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize them, it will be convenient to ſet down the Names of the Principal Officers of the Fleet.</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>Henery Bielek,</hi> Lord High Admiral.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Niels Juel,</hi> General Admiral.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Monſieur <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lgerwindt,</hi> Vice Admiral.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Monſieur Rodenſtein</hi> Rere-Admiral.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Seaſtidt,</hi> alſo Rere-Admiral, and Commiſſioner General of the <hi>Holm.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The ſtanding Army of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> conſiſts of the Guards <hi>du</hi> Corps of the Kings, Queens, and Queen Mother, and of a Company of reformed Officers, all Gentlemen, who in Buff-Coats, with Embroidered Sleeves, attend upon the King at Court, and upon all great Solemnities with gilt Partizans, Feathers in their Hats, reſembling much the Band of our Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen Penſioners. Of the following Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, with the Officers and Major-Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals, having their Quarters as is here ſet down.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:151645:22"/>
               <head>Zealand.</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schack</hi> Governour of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of a Regiment of Foot.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marſaack</hi> of Horſe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Van Oſten</hi> Collonel of a Regiment of Foot.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Funen.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Van Asken</label> 
                  <hi>Infantry.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Juitland.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Leventzo</label> 
                  <hi>Cavalry.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Laland.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Merherin.</label> 
                  <hi>Cavalry.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Norway.</head>
               <item>
                  <label>Duncam</label> 
                  <hi>Cavalry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Degenfelt</label> 
                  <hi>Infantry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Leyenhielm.</label> 
                  <hi>Infantry.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Baron Wallis,</label> Collonel of the Kings Regiment.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Schonburg</label> of the Queens.</item>
               <item>
                  <label>Meldrum</label> Prince <hi>Fredericks.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Fox</label> Prince <hi>Chriſtians.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Major Genereral <hi>Schack.</hi>
                  </label> Prince <hi>Georges.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>General <hi>Weddell.</hi>
                  </label> 
                  <hi>Jutland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Petto</label> 
                  <hi>Zealand.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Riſſel</label> 
                  <hi>Funen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <label>Frizen.</label> 
                  <hi>Holſtein.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>With ſome others, whereof we have not the Names, there being daily Changes made in reforming ſome, and raiſing others, making up in all a Body of about 30000 Men.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:151645:23"/>
The Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> ſince the Reformation made in that State, in the year 1660 hath a Perogative of as large extent as any Monarch in Chriſtendom, having Power without conſulting the States, or his Senate to <hi>Declare War, make Peace, ſend and receive Ambaſſadors, make Leagues and Treaties with any Foreign States, Iſſue out Commiſſions for the Raiſing of Men both by Sea and Land,</hi> diſpoſe of all Caſtles, Fortreſſes, Ports, Havens, Ships of War, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gazines, Ammunition, and publick Moneys; appoint the Mettal, Weight, Purity and Value thereof, and by His Order can make any Foreign Coyn, to be the cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Money of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He can by his Letters Patent, Erect <hi>New Diſtricts, Biſhopricks, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, Cities, Burroughs, Colledges, Hoſpitals, Schools, Fairs, Markets, Courts of Juſtice, Forreſts, Chaſes, Free-Warrens,</hi> He can Enfranchiſe an Alien, and render him a <hi>Deniſon,</hi> Enabling him to purchaſe Houſes and Lands, and bear Offices. He can al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo lay what Taxes he thinks fitting, upon ihs Subjects without the previous conſent of the States or Senate, Rating it Diſtrict Town or Perſon at his Pleaſure. He can at his Will and Pleaſure, Convene, Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journ, Prorogue, Remove the States and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:151645:23"/>the Senate; Grant ſafe Conduct, Letters of Mart and Reprizal with all the other Perogatives of an Independent Prince, nay, of one whoſe Will is a Law.</p>
            <p>The King of <hi>Denmark</hi> has all ſuch things as are proper <hi>To a Monarch, as Crowns, Scepters, Purple Robe,</hi> and <hi>Holy <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nction,</hi> and acknowledgeth no Superiour but God, nor holdeth his Kingdom in Vaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, nor receiveth his Inveſtiture or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalment from another. Thus at the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs of <hi>Nimeguen,</hi> there being a diſpute between the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Daniſh</hi> Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, about the Language they were to Treat in, the <hi>French</hi> Inſiſting to Love both Parties, uſe <hi>French,</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, that if the <hi>French</hi> uſed the <hi>French,</hi> they would uſe <hi>Daniſh;</hi> Being well aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that their Maſter yielded in nothing to the <hi>French</hi> King, either as to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of his Perogative or of his Dominions. And ſince the Introduction and Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in <hi>Denmark</hi> of the <hi>Augsbourg</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, there lyes no Appeal from the King to the Pope, as there does in the Catholick Princes Dominions, but He is Supream Head and Governour, in all mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters as well Eccleſiaſtical as Civil; ſo that none of his Subjects whatſoever are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from his Juriſdiction and Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:151645:24"/>
Hardly any Prince in <hi>Europe</hi> is looked upon with more Veneration and Reſpect than this Monarch is by his Subjects, they paying him all thoſe Reſpectuous Duties, Devoirs and Reverence that a Sovereign can Receive.</p>
            <p>But before I proceed any further, I ſhall give an account of the Royal Family as it Standeth at this day, as alſo of the Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and other Orders of the Kingdom. And having already ſaid that the King Married <hi>Charlotra Amalia,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>William</hi> the Sixth <hi>Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe Caſſel,</hi> in the year 1669, He hath had by that Princeſs, the following Iſſue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederick</hi> the Heir apparent Born on the 21ſt. of <hi>October,</hi> 1671.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtianus Wilhelmus,</hi> Born on the 21ſt. of <hi>November</hi> 1672. Dyed on the 25 of <hi>January</hi> 1673.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Born on the 25th. of <hi>March,</hi> 1678.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sophia Hedwig</hi> Bom on the 28. of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt,</hi> 1677.</p>
            <p>Since that Princeſs a younger Daughter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Carolus,</hi> Born in the Year 1682. or the Queen Mother, <hi>Sophia Amalia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Prince <hi>George</hi> the preſent Kings Brother, was Born in the year 1653. a Prince of extraordinary Vertues and Qualifications, and all the Actions of whoſe Life, both in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:151645:24"/>Peace and War, have ſhown Wiſdom, Valour, and Conduct, and more particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly he gave extraordinary Teſtimonies of his Gallantry and Courage, in the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel of <hi>Lunden,</hi> when that the King his Brother being taken Priſoner by the <hi>Sweeds,</hi> notwithſtanding that the Enemies far Sur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed 'em in number, that his Men were diſheartned and over-powered; Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs he ruſh'd in amongſt them, cut his way through all Oppoſition, and Slew thoſe Perſons with his own Hand, who had dared to lay hold on his Royal Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; And thus delivered the King from his Enemies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anna Sophia</hi> the King of <hi>Denmark's</hi> El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt Siſter, was born on the firſt of <hi>Septem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> in the year 1647. and was Married in <hi>September</hi> 1663. to <hi>John George</hi> the Third of the Name, Prince Electoral of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Son of the Elector <hi>John George,</hi> and of <hi>Magdelena Sibyla</hi> Marchio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Brandenbourg.</hi> And their Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age was conſummated at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> on the 16 of <hi>October,</hi> 1666.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederica Amalia,</hi> Born 1648. was Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried at <hi>Gluckſtadt</hi> on the 3d. of <hi>November</hi> 1667. to <hi>Chriſtian Adolph,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Holſtein Sunderbourg,</hi> the Son of the Duke <hi>John Chriſtian,</hi> and of <hi>Dorothea Johanna</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Swarthenbourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:151645:25"/>
               <hi>Wilhelmina Erneſtina,</hi> Born on the 20 of <hi>June</hi> 1650. and Married to the preſent Elector <hi>Palatine</hi> in the year 1671.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lrica Eleonora Sabina</hi> the Third Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, Born in the year — and Married to the preſent King of <hi>Sweeden</hi> in 1680. of the Ceremonies and Solemnization of whoſe Marriage more hereafter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederick Guldenlieu,</hi> Vice Roy of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> the late Kings Natural Son.</p>
            <p>Having thus ſpoken of the Kings Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and Brothers. I ſhall now proceed to ſet down the Princes of the Blood, and other Branches of the Royal Family, which form Sire Branches.</p>
            <p>All theſe Princes are Iſſued from <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> the 3d. King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> except the Branches of <hi>Oytin</hi> and of <hi>Golterp,</hi> which come from <hi>Adolph</hi> Duke of <hi>Heſwick,</hi> that ſame Kings Brother.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunderbourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Adilphe</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> Heir of <hi>Norway.</hi> Duke of <hi>Heſwick,</hi> of <hi>Hoſtein Sunderbourg,</hi> of <hi>Stormaria</hi> and <hi>Dithmarſh,</hi> was Born the 3d. of <hi>June</hi> 1641. of Duke <hi>John Chriſtian,</hi> (who Died the 20th. of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſt</hi> 1659.) Married at <hi>Geluckſtadt</hi> the 3d. of <hi>November</hi> in the year 1667. <hi>Frederices Emilia</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the 2d. Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:151645:25"/>of King <hi>Frederick</hi> the 3d. and of <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia Amalia,</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Lunenburg</hi> his Wife. He has two Siſters.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorothea Auguſta</hi> Born on the 12th. of <hi>September</hi> 1636. and <hi>Chriſtina Elizabetha</hi> Born on the 9th. of <hi>June,</hi> 1638. Married in the year 1656. with <hi>John Erneſt,</hi> Duke of <hi>Sax-Weymar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Alexander Henry,</hi> the Uncle of Duke <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Adolphus</hi> Born 1608. <hi>Erneſt Gunther, Alexanders</hi> Brother, Born 1609. Married <hi>Auguſta</hi> of <hi>Holſtein Glucks<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> the Daughter of Duke <hi>Philip,</hi> and of <hi>Sophia Hedwig</hi> of <hi>Sax-Sawenbourg</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>George Frederick,</hi> Born in the year, 1611.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtus Philip</hi> likewiſe, Brother of <hi>Alexander,</hi> Born in the year 1612. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried in 1645. <hi>Calrai</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> the Daughter of Count <hi>Anthony,</hi> who Died 1647. and in Second Nuptials, <hi>Sidonia</hi> her Siſter, (who Died 1650) and in the Third <hi>Maria Sibylla,</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Naſſaw;</hi> the Daughter of Count <hi>William Lewis:</hi> Of which Marriages, He has not hitherto had any Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip Lewis,</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Sunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> the Brother of thoſe Princes, Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel of a Regiment of Foot againſt the <hi>Turk</hi> in the year 1662. was Born on the 27 of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:151645:26"/>
               <hi>October</hi> 1620. and had for his firſt Wife on the 15th of <hi>November</hi> 1643. <hi>Catharina</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Waldeck</hi> the Widow of <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lewis Count de Lippe,</hi> the Daughter of <hi>Count Chriſtian,</hi> who departed this Life 1649. and was a Second time Married in the year 1650. to <hi>Anna Margarita, Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravinne</hi> of <hi>Heſſ-Hombourg,</hi> and of <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garita Elizabetha</hi> Counteſs of <hi>Leiningen</hi> from whom Iſſued two Sons and three Daughters. <hi>Sophia Catharina</hi> their Siſter born in the year 1617. Married in the year 1635. to <hi>Anthony Gunther,</hi> Died with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Norbourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Norbourg,</hi> the Uncle of the Duke of <hi>Sunderbourg,</hi> was Born on the 26th of <hi>November</hi> 1581. of Duke <hi>John,</hi> and of his firſt Wife, <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Brunſwick:</hi> the firſt Wife he Married in the year 1627. was <hi>Juliana</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Saxe-Lawenbourg,</hi> the Daughter of Duke <hi>Francis;</hi> and of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> his Second Wife, who Died 1630. and he again Married in 1632. <hi>Eleonora,</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> the Daughter of Prince <hi>Rodolph Zerbſt,</hi> and of <hi>Dorothy Hedwige</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> his firſt Wife. He died 1658. Firſt Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Bugiſlas,</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſpein Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:151645:26"/>Born 1629. on the 30th. of <hi>Septemb.</hi> Second Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elizabeth Juliana,</hi> Born 1634. Married 1656. <hi>Anthony <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lrick</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick,</hi> the Son of <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Duke of <hi>Brunſwick, Wolphembuttel,</hi> and of <hi>Dorothy</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Anhalt</hi> his Second Wife.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorothea Hedwig,</hi> Born 1636. <hi>Doyene</hi> of <hi>Ganderſheim.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian Auguſtus,</hi> Born 1639.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ludorica Amalia,</hi> Born 1642.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rodolphus Frederick,</hi> Born 1645.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gluckbourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philip</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Gluckbourg,</hi> the Grand Uncle of Duke <hi>Chriſtian Auguſtus,</hi> was Born 1584. and died 1663. being the Brother of Duke <hi>Frederick</hi> above mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Born of the firſt Bed. Married in the year 1624. <hi>Sophia Hedwig,</hi> Dutches of <hi>Saxe-La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wenbourg,</hi> the Daughter of Duke <hi>Frareis,</hi> and of <hi>Mary</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Brunſwick</hi> his Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Wife, of which Marriage are Born.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Born in 1627. and dyed 1671.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary-Elizabeth,</hi> Born in the year 1628. Married 1651. to <hi>George Albert</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenbourg,</hi> and dyed 1664.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Adolphe,</hi> Born 1631.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſta,</hi> Born 1633. Married in 1651. to <hi>Erneſt Gunther</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Sunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg</hi> her Couſin, the Son of Duke <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:151645:27"/>and of the Dutcheſs <hi>Dorothey</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſs of <hi>Schwartrenbourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtina</hi> Born 1634. Married 1650.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Duke of <hi>Saxony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Dorothy,</hi> Born 1636. Married for the firſt time in the year 1653. <hi>Chriſtian Lew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>is</hi> Duke of <hi>Lunenbourg,</hi> and the Second on the 25th. of <hi>June</hi> 1668. <hi>Frederick Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam</hi> Marqueſs of <hi>Brandenbourg</hi> Elector.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hedwig,</hi> Born 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleonor</hi> Dutches of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> Siſter of <hi>Philip,</hi> Born 1590.</p>
            <p>Second Bed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hedwig</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Dorothy,</hi> Born 1643.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anna Sabina,</hi> the Dutcheſs of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> Born in the year 1593. of the Second Bed of Duke <hi>John,</hi> of his Second Wiſe, <hi>Agnes-Hedwig,</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> Married 1698. <hi>Julius Frederick,</hi> Duke of <hi>Wirtembourg</hi> the Son of Duke <hi>Frederick,</hi> Count of <hi>Mont<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beliard</hi> who left her a Widow. &amp; died 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Arnſbeck.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Joachim Erneſt</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein-Arnſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beck,</hi> Born in the year 1595. of <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Sleſwick</hi> and of <hi>Holſtein Sunderbourg,</hi> and of his Second Wife <hi>Agnes Hedwig</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> Born in the year 1595. Married in 1633. <hi>Dorothea Auguſta</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Holſtein leſwick</hi> his Couſin,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:151645:27"/>the Daughter of Duke <hi>John Adolphus,</hi> and of the Princeſs <hi>Auguſta</hi> of <hi>Denmark,</hi> He Dyed 1671. but had by that Princeſs <hi>John Adolphus,</hi> in 1634. General Major of the Imperial Cavalry againſt the <hi>Turks</hi> in 1664.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> Born in 1639. <hi>Erneſtina</hi> in 1636. <hi>Joachim Erneſt,</hi> 1637. <hi>Bernard,</hi> 1639. <hi>Agnes Hedwig,</hi> 1640. <hi>Sophia Eleonor,</hi> 1644.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eleonor Sophia,</hi> the Siſter of <hi>Joachim Erneſt,</hi> Born 1603. of the Second Bed: Married in the year 1625. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the young Prince of <hi>Anhalt,</hi> the Son of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt Barnbourg,</hi> whoſe Widow ſhe is.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gottorp.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Frederick</hi> Duke of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> of <hi>Holſtein Gottorp,</hi> of <hi>Stormaria,</hi> of <hi>Dithmars,</hi> Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin <hi>German,</hi> of Duke <hi>Joachim Erneſt,</hi> Born 1697. of Duke <hi>John Adolphus,</hi> and of <hi>Auguſta</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Denmark,</hi> Married in the year 1630. <hi>Mary-Elizabeth,</hi> Dutch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſs of <hi>Saxony,</hi> the Daughter of the Elector, <hi>John George,</hi> and of <hi>Magdalena Sibila</hi> of <hi>Brandenbourg Pruſſia</hi> of which Alliance are Born the following Children. In the year 1633. this Prince ſent a ſignal Embaſſy into <hi>Muſcovy &amp; into Perſia</hi> for the Eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Commerce by Land. He Alternates with the King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:151645:28"/>the Admiſtration of Juſtice, in the Seſſion at the Dyets of the Empire, and in all the Rights of the <hi>Regale.</hi> He Died the 10 of <hi>Aug.</hi> 1659.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sophia Auguſta,</hi> Born 1630. Married, 1649. with <hi>John</hi> Prince of <hi>Anhalt Zerbſt,</hi> the Son of Prince <hi>Rodolphus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magdalena Sibila,</hi> Born 1631. Married in the year 1654. to <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus,</hi> Duke of <hi>Mecklembourg,</hi> the Son of Duke <hi>John Albert.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mary Elizabeth,</hi> Born 1634. Married in the year 1650, to <hi>Lewis Landgrave</hi> of <hi>Heſſe Darmſtadt,</hi> the Son of the <hi>Landgrave George</hi> the Second.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hedwig Eleonor,</hi> Born 1636. on the 23 of <hi>October,</hi> Married in the year 1654. on the 24 of <hi>October, Carolus Guſtavus</hi> King of <hi>Sweeden,</hi> the Son of <hi>John Caſimir</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of the <hi>Rhine,</hi> and of <hi>Katharina</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Sweeden,</hi> Siſter of King <hi>Guſtavus Adolphus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anna Dorothea,</hi> Born 1640. <hi>Auguſtus Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick,</hi> Born 1646. <hi>Auguſta Maria,</hi> 1649.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ottingen</hi> or <hi>Oyten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>John Auguſtus</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Ottin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen,</hi> Nephew of Duke <hi>Frederick Gottorp,</hi> Born 1647. on the third of <hi>Auguſt,</hi> the Son of <hi>John</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Ottingen,</hi> or <hi>Oyten,</hi> and of <hi>Juliana Felecita</hi> Dutcheſs of <hi>Wirtembourg.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:151645:28"/>
               <hi>Dorothea Auguſta,</hi> Siſter of Duke <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derick Gottorp,</hi> Born 1602. Married in 1633. <hi>Joachim Erneſt</hi> Duke of <hi>Holſtein Arnſbourg,</hi> Her Couſin the Son of Duke <hi>John,</hi> and of his Second Wife <hi>Agnes Hed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wig,</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Anhalt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hedwig</hi> Siſter of <hi>Dorothea,</hi> Born in 1603. Married in 1620. with <hi>Auguſtus</hi> Count <hi>Palatine</hi> of <hi>Sultzbach,</hi> the Son of <hi>Philip Lewis,</hi> Count <hi>Palatine,</hi> Duke of <hi>Newbourg,</hi> and <hi>Ann</hi> of <hi>Cleves,</hi> and of <hi>Juliers,</hi> Died in 1656.</p>
            <p>And I ſhall paſs on to the Nobles, who never Claim, nor pretend to the Titles of Dukes, Earls, or Barons, but are ſuch as have had a ſingle Coat of Arms belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to their Family for many Ages. <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> is ſaid to have at this day, ſome Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of that Nobility, of that antiquity as <hi>VVren</hi> and others, as to have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, at the Signing of a Treaty of Peace between <hi>Charles Magne</hi> and the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King <hi>Hemmines</hi> on the <hi>Eider.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Out of this Body of the Nobility, are drawn the Senators of the Kingdom, or the Members of the Council of State, who are Elected to the Number of 28. All a No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemans Goods, moveable and immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are at his Death divided amongſt his Children, the Son having two Moities, and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:151645:29"/>a Daughter only one. The King cannot by the Laws of <hi>Denmark,</hi> purchaſe any part of a Noble-Mans Eſtate, neither can the Nobles buy any of the Crown Lands, ſome Officers of the Crown, Knights of the Order of the <hi>Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phant;</hi> Vice-Roys and Governours of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinces and Places, were formerly choſen out of the Body of the Nobility, and nominated by the Election of the Senators, bating the Knights of the Order: But at preſent, ſince the Reformation of that Kingdom, half of thoſe Officers are drawn out of the Body of the Burgery, the King being willing to conſider, and Reward that part of the State, which ſerved with ſo much Courage and fidelity at the Siege of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> when that Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital of the Kingdom, was almoſt the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place which ſuſtained almoſt all Efforts of the <hi>Sweediſh</hi> Army, which had taken in all the reſt of the Kingdom. But here I will Inſert a Catalogue of the Principal Families of the Nobility now in <hi>Denmark,</hi> in the following Alphabetical Order.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:151645:29"/>
               <head>A</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Achſel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Appelgard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Alefeld.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Anderſem.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bielke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Banner.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brache.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bilig.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Below.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bilde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brokenhuſem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biorn.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beck.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Blick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baſſi.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bax.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baſelich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bille.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bilde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bockowlt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Budde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baggen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bammelbourg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Blom.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brocktorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Breiden</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dreſlelberch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Daac.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dune.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Duram.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dam.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Freze.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faſſi.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Falſter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Faleke.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>G</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gulderſtern.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grubbe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Goce.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Green.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gelſchut.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Galle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gram.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gris.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Goſs.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Gadendorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Grahow.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hardenberg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hoken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hiderſtorper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hiderſtorper.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hube.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Heſten.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hager.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Holer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Haeken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hoier.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hacken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Harberger.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jul.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Jenſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Juenan.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Juenſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Johenſen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Korwitz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Krabbe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kaas.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kruſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kragge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Krumpen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kramdick.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kerckberg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Karſſenbrock.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Kaelet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:151645:30"/>
                  <hi>Kutzen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lindeman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lunge.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lutkem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Laxman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lancken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leven.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Luck.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lindow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lutken.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Munck.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Matieſſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Marizer.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Muſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Matre.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Meinſtorf.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Maeten.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Magnuſſen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Negil.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Narbu.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Norman.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ofrin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Otten.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paſberg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Podeſſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Podebuſſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Papenheimb.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pogwiſch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pleſſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Paiſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Peterſen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>Q</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Qualem.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Quittow.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Rantzaw.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſentkrantz.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Raſtorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ruthede.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reuter.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ruten.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſenpart.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roſengard.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Roanow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Reventlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ratlow.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ritzerow.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schram.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schefeldt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Schelen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Seestede.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stuege.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swron.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stantbeke.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Split.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Solle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Swaben.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Santbarch.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spar.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spegel.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sturen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Suinen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Staken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Stove.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Siverſerſen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Trolle.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tolten.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:151645:30"/>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wlefeld.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Walkendorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wipfert.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Witfelt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wogerſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wenflterman.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wolde.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worm.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Walstorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wenſin.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wiltorp.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whrup.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vonsflet.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Vartinnen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>oien.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lstandt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ren.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Tho till ſome of late Creation, the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Nobles had neither the Titles of Dutchies, Marquiſſates, Counties, nor Barrony, as other States; nor do they Quarter their Armes, yet tis Cuſtomary for many of them to be Dub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Knights, upon any Signal piece of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice rendred to their Prince or Countrey.</p>
            <p>Two Orders of Knight-hood they have in <hi>Denmark,</hi> that of the <hi>Elephant</hi> and that of <hi>Dancbrogh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That of the <hi>Elephant</hi> was firſt inſtituted upon the occaſion of King <hi>Christian</hi> the firſt going in a kind of Pilgrimage to <hi>Rome,</hi> when as he was inveſted by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth with this Order, in Remembrance of our Lord and Saviour, and at the ſame time it was Ordain'd that the Succeeding Kings of <hi>Denmark,</hi> ſhould have a Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Right to be Soveraigns of this Order. Whereupon the foreſaid King <hi>Christian,</hi> Built the Stately Chappel of the three
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:151645:31"/>Kings, in the Cathedral at <hi>Roſchildt</hi> where the ſolemnities of the Order were to be held, and the Knights obliged to Aſſemble, for the chooſing a new Member upon the Death of any of their Fraternity. Into the Number whereof ſeveral Kings, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Noble Men have been Admitted. The chief Enſigne of the Order, was the Figure of an <hi>Elephant,</hi> on whoſe ſide (within a Rundle) was repreſented a Crown of Thorns, with three Nails all Bloody; in Honour and Memory of the Paſſion of our Bleſſed Saviour. The Knights were obliged to the performance of Acts of Piety, <hi>Alms-deeds,</hi> and certain Ceremonies particularly on thoſe days on which they wore the Enſignes of their Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Some of the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> have been very Zealous to raiſe the Honour of this Order to the Higheſt Eſteem, and eſpecially their King <hi>John,</hi> who wore the Enſignes of it on every Solemn Feſtival, and ſo promoted its value, that our King <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight, and King <hi>James</hi> the Fifth of <hi>Scotland,</hi> were content to be of the Fraternity. Some <hi>Daniſh</hi> Writers are not of Opinion, that it re eived its firſt Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, when <hi>Christian</hi> the Firſt had thoſe many Honours conferr'd on him by Pope <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth, but that the Badge
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:151645:31"/>was a meer Millitary Enſigne, formerly beſtowed as a Memorial and Incite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Princes, for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence and promoting of Chriſtianity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Infidels. Heretofore the Knights wore a Collar of Gold, Compoſed of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lephants</hi> and <hi>Croſſes,</hi> faſhioned ſomewhat like <hi>Croſſes Ancrees,</hi> at which Hung the Picture of the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> to the middle holding <hi>Christ</hi> in Her Arms, and ſurround<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <hi>Glory</hi> of Sun Beams. But at this day they only wear a Blew Ribbond, at which hangs an <hi>Elephant Enamell'd</hi> white, Adorned with four large Diamonds ſet in the middle. Thoſe <hi>Elephants</hi> worn by the Knights, in the days of <hi>Christian</hi> the Fourth, had in the ſame place within a Circle the Letter <hi>C.</hi> and in the Heart thereof the figure of 4. made to ſignifie <hi>Christianus Quartus.</hi> The Kings of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> have Generally conferred this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour on the days of their Coronation, both upon the Nobles and Senatours of the Kingdome. <hi>Frederick</hi> the Third, brought into uſe an Embroidered <hi>Glory</hi> of Silver Purl, wrought upon the left ſide of their Cloak or Veſt, on which was Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broidered two Crowns within a Rundle, bearing this <hi>Motto, Deus Providebit.</hi> But the <hi>Motto</hi> has changed with the Soveraign,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:151645:32"/>for that of the preſent King is <hi>Pietate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> justitia;</hi> and this the Knights of his Creation now Wear in the middle of the Circle; B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all the Knights of his Fathers making, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obliged to continue ſtill the former <hi>Mott<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Order of <hi>Danebroge,</hi> or the Knight of the Holy Croſs, was inſtituted in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of the Croſs, which is ſaid mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly to have fallen into, and preſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed King <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Second's Army when that having loſt their Standard, his Forces were going to yield, and give themſelves up a Prey to the Fury of their <hi>Pagan</hi> Enemies the <hi>Lifelanders,</hi> with vvhom they were then Combating. This Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> was Continued till the Relique was loſt it ſolfe in <hi>Ditmarſh,</hi> after which it was for a long while wholly laid aſide, until revived again in the year 1673. by the preſent King <hi>Christian</hi> the Fifth. This Prince ordain'd that the Knights of this Order, of which Himſelf is one, ſhould Wear an Enamell'd Croſs Edg'd round with Red, hung in a ſtring of the ſame Colour, reaching from the Right Shoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to the Left ſide.</p>
            <p>Out of the Nobility, and the Knights, the Senators of the Kingdom were former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly choſen, who anciently ſeldome exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:151645:32"/>the Numbers of Eight, but now are a far greater Number. As long as they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in their places, they were main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd by the Country; They had Caſtles allowed to dwell in (by the King) paid no Taxes, were only obliged to keep a certain number of Light Horſe ready for Service upon all Occaſions, and attend upon the King at his Sunimous, upon their own Charges, though not Bound ſo to do, if he went out of his Dominions, and if ſent upon Embaſſy's, had an Allowance out of the Treaſury.</p>
            <p>Beſides theſe, were Penſioners, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good Services Rendered the Crown, had certain Lands for Life or a ſet number of Years Aſſigned them by the King for their Maintenance; In conſideration of which, they were to provide ſo many Light Horſe as the King thought fitting, and pay in Annually a certain Sum of Money into the Exchequer. But ſince the Reformation of the Government in the year 1660. The number of them is very much Retrenched.</p>
            <p>The Principal Officers of the Crown of <hi>Denmark,</hi> are choſen from out amongſt the Nobility and Senators.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:151645:33"/>
The Firſt is the <hi>Grand-Maſter</hi> of the Kingdom, who is as the Kings Lieutenant.</p>
            <p>The Second <hi>Holger Windt,</hi> the Lord High Treaſurer, who receives in, and gives Acquittances for all Sums paid into the Kings <hi>Exchequer,</hi> and has under him two Secretaries of the Nobility, and a great Number of Inferiour Clarks.</p>
            <p>The Third the Lord High Chancellor, <hi>Henry Alefelt</hi> Count of <hi>Exingen</hi> and <hi>Lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe Office is much the ſame as in other Kingdoms.</p>
            <p>The Fourth the Grand Marſhal, who provides neceſſaries for all manner of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patches, in the times of War and Peace. This Office is now enjoyed by <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>an Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtopher Corbitz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Lord High Admiral <hi>Henry Bielek.</hi> Knight of the Order of the Elephant; who take; care of the Building and Reparing of all ſorts of Ships belonging to the Crown. He had under him a Vice-Admiral, <hi>Niel Juel,</hi> who Acts by his Commiſſion, with Baron <hi>Jens Juel,</hi> and Mounſieur <hi>Rodenſtein</hi> Rear Admirals; And Mounſieur <hi>Seaſtede</hi> Commiſſary General of the <hi>Holm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Grand-Maſter of the Artillery.</p>
            <p>The Maſter of the Horſe, Mounſieur <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>huiſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Great Cup-Bearer.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:151645:33"/>
Mounſieur <hi>Knoel</hi> the Firſt Gentleman of the Kings Bed-Chamber.</p>
            <p>Meſſ.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sebulter</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Bierman</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Secretaries of State.</p>
            <p>Meſſ.
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sehuller</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Jeſſen.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
Secretaries to the King.</p>
            <p>In the year 1660. the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> Eſtabliſhed Seven Councils: The Firſt of State, wherein their Great-Maſter the King preſides, and which Sits-once a Year. The Second of the Finances, wherein the Lord High Treaſurer Sits as Preſident. The Third the Chancery, wherein the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor Preſides. The Fourth of the <hi>Militia</hi> wherein the Lord High Marſhal Preſides. The Fifth of Juſtice, wherein Preſides. <hi>N.</hi> The Sixth of the Admiralty, wherein Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Admiral; And the Seventh of the Commerce.</p>
            <p>Under the Vice-Roy of <hi>Norway, Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick</hi> Count <hi>Guldenlew,</hi> Knight of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the <hi>Elephant,</hi> and Natural Son of the late King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> there be Five particular Governments.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. That of <hi>Bahus,</hi> the moſt <hi>Southern</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, but now under the <hi>Sweed</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:151645:34"/>
2. Of <hi>Argerhus,</hi> Seaten in the Gulph of <hi>Anſloo</hi> or <hi>Opſlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> a Biſhops See.</item>
               <item>3. Of <hi>Berghen,</hi> a Biſhops See.</item>
               <item>4. Of <hi>Drunthecim</hi> or <hi>Tronthecim</hi> an Arch-Biſhoprick.</item>
               <item>5. Of <hi>Wardhus,</hi> the laſt place of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> and of Chriſtendome, Lying towards the <hi>North,</hi> Scated in the Iſle of <hi>Ward.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>The Governments of the Provinces and Places of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </head>
               <item>Of <hi>Juitland,</hi> Mounſieur <hi>Lavenzo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Holſtein</hi> N.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Copenhaghen,</hi> Mounſieur <hi>Sehack.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Cronenburg</hi> Mounſieur <hi>Oſten.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the County N. N.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Pinnenburg.</hi> N. N.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Dithmarſe</hi> N. N.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Starmaria</hi> N. N.</item>
               <item>Of <hi>Wagerland</hi> or <hi>Wagria.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Finmark.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Iſle of <hi>Funen,</hi> M. G. <hi>Van Aſken.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Iſle of <hi>Bornholm.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Iſle of <hi>Iſland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Iſle of <hi>Greenland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of <hi>Spitzbergen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>There are only Seaven Biſhopricks in <hi>Denmark;</hi> which are all in the Kings diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal.</p>
            <list>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:151645:34"/>
               <item>1. <hi>Copenhaghen,</hi> Whereof the Biſhop has Arch-Piſcopal Rights, but not the Title.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Ripen.</hi> and both in the <hi>Nor. Juitland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Arhuſen.</hi> both in the <hi>Nor. Juitland.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Odenſee</hi> in the Iſle of <hi>Funen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Wiburg.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>6. <hi>Arhuſen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>7. <hi>Sleſwick.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The Arch Biſhop of <hi>Trunthein</hi> or <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thein</hi> in the <hi>North</hi> of the Kingdom of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> where is ſtill ſeen the remains of the moſt Magnificent Church of the <hi>North,</hi> Dedicated to <hi>S. Olaus.</hi> This Arch Biſhop had the following Suffragan Biſhops.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Bergen</hi> the Metropolis of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom upon the Sea.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>Staffanger</hi> upon the Shoar of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Ocean.</item>
               <item>3. <hi>Hammar</hi> Reunited to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Anſloo.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Anſloo</hi> or <hi>Opſloo</hi> above <hi>Bahuys.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. <hi>Sodre</hi> an Iſland.</item>
               <item>6. <hi>Greenland</hi> an Iſland.</item>
               <item>7. <hi>Schalholt</hi> an Iſland.</item>
               <item>8. <hi>Hola</hi> or <hi>Kola,</hi> in the moſt <hi>Northern</hi> part of <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:151645:35"/>
But at this day the Biſhopricks of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> are reduced to Four, Namely,</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Bergen.</hi> 2. <hi>Steinamanger.</hi> 3. <hi>Dron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thein.</hi> 4. <hi>Chriſtiana,</hi> under whoſe Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction the reſt are brought, unleſs ſome under <hi>Copenhaghen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Denmark</hi> has produc'd many Men Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their Learning, and beſides the <hi>Bards</hi> or <hi>Druids,</hi> we have accounts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other kinds of Poets and Learned Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons amongſt the ancient <hi>Danes.</hi> Some Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors tell us the ſeveral ſorts of Verſes com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by the <hi>Scialdrae</hi> and <hi>Runae</hi> are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable; but may be at leaſt the beſt of them, Reduced to 36 Heads. It was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly the cuſtom of all the <hi>Northern</hi> Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to have the Genealogies and Famous, Deeds of their Anceſtors, put into Dog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerell, that being daily chanted over by the Parents to their Children, they might be the eaſier Remembred and Tranſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Poſterity. The Compoſers of theſe Ballads were the Grandees of the Nation, and looked upon as the Princes Wiſeſt Councellors. Nay, ſome for the Reward of a Song, or an Epitaph have been preſented with the Crown of <hi>Denmark.</hi> But as it would be an endleſs matter to ſet down all the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Authors, we ſhall content our ſelves with Inſerting the following Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:151645:35"/>
               <hi>Saxo Grammaticus,</hi> who Writ the Hiſtory of <hi>Denmark,</hi> in a moſt Elegant Stile, and Lived in the Twelſth Centuary.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Eraſmus Latus,</hi> Profeſſor of Divinity in the Univerſity of <hi>Copenhaghen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Nicolaus Hemmingius</hi> noted for his Ingenious Commentaries upon the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Nobleman, Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for his Admirable Obſervations in Aſtronomy.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second, gave him the Iſland <hi>Ween,</hi> where <hi>Tycho</hi> built his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourg,</hi> about the year 1575 being an obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vatory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the form of a Caſtle, and Fenced round with regular Fortifications, and which he finding a place remote from all troubles, and a fit retirement for a Student, he Adorned it with a Collection of the moſt exact Mathematical Inſtruments that could be procured.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Christianus ſeverini Longomontanus</hi> was Bred up in the Science of <hi>Astronomy,</hi> by <hi>Tycho Brahe,</hi> and has written ſeveral Inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious pieces thereof.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Arrild Witfield,</hi> Lord of <hi>Orderſberch</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced, <hi>Saxo</hi>'s Hiſtory to a Chronological method and Compoſed an accurate Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle of the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> in the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Tongue.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:151645:36"/>
7. <hi>Stephanus Stephanius,</hi> Profeſſor of Hiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ory in the Univerſity of <hi>Sor</hi> has Illuſtrated <hi>Saxo Gramaticus</hi> with Ingenious Annota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and writ an Account of the State of <hi>Denmark</hi> during the Reign of <hi>Christian</hi> the Third.</p>
            <p n="8">8. <hi>Olaus Wormius</hi> has made a Rare Colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of Natural Curioſities, and great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coveries into the Miſterious <hi>Runick</hi> Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p n="9">9. <hi>Petrus Johannes Reſenius,</hi> a great Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quary, as may be ſeen by His <hi>Edda Iſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorum,</hi> and other Curious pieces.</p>
            <p>To theſe may be added, <hi>Petrus Severi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Borrichius,</hi> the two <hi>Bartholins,</hi> the one of whom <hi>Gaſper Bartholinis</hi> ſuppoſed to have made the Dial of the Cathedral of <hi>Lunden</hi> in <hi>Schonen,</hi> which Dial ſhows the Year, Month, Week, Day, and Hour of the Day, all at the ſame time; with all Feaſts both Moveable and fixed, as alſo the Motions of the Sun and Moon, and their Progreſs through every Degree of the <hi>Zodiack.</hi> This Clock is ſo Ordered by Artificial Engines, that when ever it ſtrikes, two Horſe-men come forth and Encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter each other, the one giving the other juſt ſo many Blows as the Hammer is to ſtrike upon the Bell: at what time a Door opening, the <hi>Virgin Mary</hi> appears, ſitting
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:151645:36"/>upon a Throne with <hi>Christ</hi> in Her Arms, and the <hi>Magi</hi> doing him Reverence, and two Trumpets Sounding all the while.</p>
            <p>And this Regiſter I ſuppoſe, is ſufficient to ſhow, how much <hi>Denmark</hi> has Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buted towards the Advancement of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
            <p>The Cittizens and Merchants form the Third Order of the Kingdome, and the Peaſants or <hi>Ruſtis,</hi> the Fourth, who are either Freeholders: ſuch as have Hereditary Eſtates, paying only ſome ſmall quit Rent to their Land-Lords or <hi>Wornede</hi> Villains, abſolutely in the Power of their Lords.</p>
            <p>The Cities are Governed by their di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct Corporations. And the Citizens enjoy peculiar Priviledges, and Charters, as in other States of <hi>Europe.</hi> Out of theſe two laſt Orders are Elected, the Arch-Biſhops, the Biſhops, the Canons, Paſtours, and Senators of Citties and other: leſſer Officers.</p>
            <p>Whilſt the Kingdome of <hi>Denmark</hi> lay confuſed and broken into ſeveral parts, all the Provinces had not all the ſame Law, but were Governed by peculiar Statutes. Whence we read of <hi>Leges Scanicae, Leges Sialandice,</hi> and the like. But when they came to be reunited under on Head, they became all Subject to the ſame Law. The
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:151645:37"/>Laws now in uſe were compiled into one Body, which they call the <hi>Iydſe Lowbog,</hi> or the Book of the Laws of <hi>Juitland,</hi> and Eſtabliſhed by King <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Second. But nevertheleſs ſometimes changed accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Circumſtances of the juncture. Thus Murder was formerly puniſhed, only with a pecuniary Mulct, but now with Death. The Ancient <hi>Danes</hi> were ſo Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, to have their Eſtates enjoyed by the right Heirs, that they puniſhed Adultery with Death; which Law is ſtill in force in <hi>Sweeden, Saxony,</hi> and many other Parts of <hi>Germany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Danes</hi> uſed formerly, and do ſtill, in ſome parts of <hi>Juitland,</hi> to Aſſemble eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Pariſh by themſelves once a Year in the Fields, to Determine all Controverſies by Twelve Select Men, from whom an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal lay to the Judge of the Province, upon the inreconciliation of the Parties, and thence to the Supream Court of Juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and this cuſtome of a Jury of Twelve Men, was undoubtedly derived to the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> from the <hi>Danes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the <hi>Heathen Danes,</hi> did likewiſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine Controverſies by Duels, wherein the Juſtice of the Cauſe was Demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the ſucceſs. But Chriſtianity Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed this Cuſtome, when one <hi>Loppo</hi> upon
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:151645:37"/>its firſt Planting, for the confirming the truth of His Doctrine, took up with his bare Hands, Glowing-Hot Barrs of Iron, without the leaſt Harm to the Admiration of all the Beholders. This Miracle wrought a change both in the Religion and Laws of the Realm, for King <hi>Sweno</hi> Ordered that thence forward, all Perſons accuſed of any Hainous Crime, ſhould clear themſelves by carrying in their Hands a Glowing <hi>Plow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhare,</hi> or ſome other piece of Hot Iron.</p>
            <p>This kind of purging is called by ſome of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Writers <hi>Jerntegn,</hi> i. e. <hi>Iron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token;</hi> by others <hi>Ordale.</hi> Our <hi>Saxon An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cestours</hi> borrowed from the <hi>Danes</hi> ſeveral kinds of <hi>Ordale,</hi> as by carrying a Barr of Hot Iron up to the High Alter Bare-Hand; by Treading Bare-foot and Blindfold over a certain number of Glowing Barrs, laid on the ground at unequal diſtance; by thruſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Naked Arm into a pot of Boyling Water; and laſtly as they uſe to try Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, by throwing the accuſed Party into a River or deep Veſſel of cold Water. The Firſt that throughly Aboliſhed all kinds of <hi>Ordale</hi> in <hi>Denmark,</hi> was King <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Second, about the year 1240. at the requeſt of <hi>Pope</hi> Innocent the Third.</p>
            <p>The Coines in uſe in <hi>Denmark</hi> are Duc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates of Gold, of the value of two <hi>Rix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dollers,</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:151645:38"/>or Crowns of Gold, of the value either of Eighteen or Nineteen Marks, or, the double of theſe. The leſſer <hi>Daniſh</hi> Coyns are 1. <hi>Huide,</hi> whereof three make one of their Shillings. 2. <hi>Soſlinger,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of two make one Shilling. 3. Shilling whereof ſixteen make a Mark. 4. A mark which is the fourth part of a <hi>Slet Dollar.</hi> 5. A <hi>Rix-Dollar,</hi> which is Six <hi>Marks,</hi> or, ninety fix Shillings.</p>
            <p>At the Solemnization of Weddings, Chriſtnings, and Buryals in <hi>Denmark,</hi> they ſpare no expences to ſeem Noble and Magnificent, ſometimes rather than want a Splendid Funeral for their Relations, they keep the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Corps for ſeveral years, and in the mean while ſcrape and heap up as much Money as will maintain the pomp of its Funeral.</p>
            <p>And now I ſhall proceed to the Topo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graphical Deſcription of each particular Place and Province of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks</hi> Dominions.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cimbrick Cherſoneſe</hi> hath on the <hi>Eaſt</hi> the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, on the <hi>Weſt,</hi> the main <hi>German</hi> Ocean, on the <hi>North</hi> a part of the bending into the narrow Streight, called the <hi>Delt,</hi> on the <hi>South,</hi> with the great River of <hi>Albis,</hi> on the <hi>South-Eaſt,</hi>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:151645:38"/>with the ſmall River of <hi>Trave,</hi> it was ſo called from the <hi>Kempers,</hi> Men of Vaſt Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies and Strength, and whom the <hi>Romans</hi> called <hi>Cimbri,</hi> the <hi>Greeks Cimmeri,</hi> and their Country <hi>Cherſoneſus Cimbrica,</hi> which Name was given to the whole Tract of Land beyond the <hi>Elb;</hi> the latter Hiſtorians con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine it to that part only, which now goeth under the Name of <hi>Juitland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is in length about 100 <hi>Italian</hi> Miles, and 80 in Breadth, and comprehendeth in that extent of Ground, 33 Walled Towns, ſix Epiſcopal Sees, (beſides thoſe of <hi>Hamburg</hi> and <hi>Lubeck</hi>) which are under the Arch Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of <hi>Bremen,</hi> and 20 Royal Caſtles and Pallaces. It is at preſent divided into the Dukedom of <hi>Holſtein</hi> and the Province of <hi>Juitland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dukedome of <hi>Holſtein</hi> went under the General Name of <hi>Nortablingia,</hi> or, the Country beyond the <hi>Elb, Northwards,</hi> and containeth thoſe four Provinces, 1. <hi>Wager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> 2. <hi>Di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>marſe.</hi> 3. <hi>Stormar.</hi> 4. <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt</hi> or <hi>Holſtein;</hi> Specially ſo called from the <hi>Dutch</hi> word <hi>Holſt,</hi> which ſignifies a Wood or Forreſt, according to the Nature of the Country.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wagerland</hi> is that part of <hi>Holſtein</hi> which lyes on the <hi>South-Eaſt</hi> of this <hi>Cherſoneſus,</hi> and ſo called from the <hi>Wagriane</hi> a Tribe or
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:151645:39"/>Nation of the <hi>Selaves,</hi> who poſſeſſed this tract The Chief Towns are, 1. <hi>Lubeck</hi> pleaſantly Seated on the Confluence of the <hi>Trave,</hi> and the <hi>Billow,</hi> the River being capable of Ships of a Thouſand Tun; This is an Imperial and <hi>Hanſe</hi> Town, driving a vaſt Trade, being Reckoned to have about 600 Ships of all ſorts, ſome of a Thouſand Tun and upwards, it is one of the beſt Built and moſt Beautiful Cities of all <hi>Germany,</hi> being in compaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſix Miles, Fortified with a double Wall, deep Ditches, and unfordable Rivers. It was made ſo Head-ſtrong by the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges conferred upon it, by the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> that it bid defiance to its Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign, and became a Dukedom of its ſelf; Tho the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> have ever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued their Claim, and it's thought the preſent Prince has now a deſigne of Vigo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly Executing his Pretentions. 2. <hi>Sege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> on the River <hi>Trave,</hi> four <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles from <hi>Lubeck,</hi> and near the Head of that River. 3. <hi>Oldeſlo,</hi> on the ſame River in the midſt betwixt both. 4. <hi>Gronneberg,</hi> and 5. <hi>Newkirk,</hi> on the <hi>Baltick</hi>-Shore: And 6. <hi>Stendorp,</hi> more within the Land, near the Edge of a Lake, out of which runs the River <hi>Suentin.</hi> 7. <hi>Ploen</hi> an Ancient City exceedingly well fortified.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:151645:39"/>
In the furtheſt Corner of <hi>Wagerland</hi> lyes the Ancient and Famous County of <hi>Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg;</hi> divided from the reſt of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince by the River <hi>Brochaw.</hi> It's principal City <hi>Oldenburg,</hi> was formerly the <hi>Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis</hi> of the <hi>Wagrians,</hi> and <hi>Venedi</hi> a Town of great Trade, and exceeding Populous, but ſince the Port was ſtopt up by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of Queen <hi>Margaret,</hi> its Splendour has daily leſſened, and by the late dreadful Deſolation, cauſed by Thunder and Light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which laid waſt the beſt and great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt part of the City, 'tis become now much leſs conſiderable than it was before: from the Princes of this Country is derived the Preſent Royal Family of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Province of <hi>Ditmarſh</hi> lyes along the <hi>German Ocean,</hi> Inhabited by People of the <hi>Saxon</hi> Race, who never could be brought under the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> until <hi>Holſtein</hi> it ſelf was annexed to the Crown of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> The Chief Towns are <hi>Meldorp</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Ocean, the chief of the Province. 2. <hi>Lunden,</hi> oppoſite to <hi>Tonningen</hi> near the mouth of the <hi>Eyder.</hi> 3. <hi>Heyde,</hi> a large but poor City.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stormar,</hi> ſo called from the <hi>Marſhy</hi> Ground lying along the River <hi>Stoer.</hi> The Principal Cities are <hi>Hamburg,</hi> upon the <hi>Bille,</hi> where it falls into the <hi>Elb,</hi> an Ancient
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:151645:40"/>Town Built in the time of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> being one of the largeſt, beſt Built, moſt Beautiful and Richeſt Cities of <hi>Europe.</hi> Upon the Right the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein</hi> had to this City, it Swore Allegiance to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Firſt, King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> which pretentions have upon all occaſions been renewed by thoſe Princes, and more particularly after the concluſion of the late Peace with <hi>Sweeden,</hi> when the preſent King drew his Army about that Town, which though not ſufficient to force ſuch a City, yet coming at firſt as near it as he pleaſed, by means of the Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourhood of <hi>Altena,</hi> raiſed Batteries for his Artillery and Bombes, with which he might have eaſily Incommoded the Town. Whereupon ſeveral Princes Vigorouſly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſing for an accommodation, it was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſionally concluded on the Firſt of <hi>Novem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 1679. The Rights of the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> and of the City of <hi>Hamburg,</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining as they were, until that the point of Homage, and the other differences, which depended betwixt his <hi>Daniſh</hi> Majeſty and that Town, ſhould in an amicable way be decided by courſe of Law. Now the chief condition of that accommodation, was an obligation by the Town of <hi>Hamburg</hi> to pay, at five Terms, to his <hi>Daniſh</hi> Majeſty, the Sum of two hundred and twenty thouſand
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:151645:40"/>Crowns; In conſideration whereof that King Remitted the Indignation he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt that Town, Renounced the Pretentions that he had to the Land Jointly poſſeſſed by <hi>Hambourg</hi> and <hi>Lubeck;</hi> and promiſed to reſtore the Ships, Goods, Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and Inhabitants of <hi>Hambourg,</hi> which had been Seized upon the account of theſe pretentions.</p>
            <p>Other Towns of Note are 1. <hi>Gluckſtadt,</hi> Built and well Fortified by King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth, and much improved by His Succeſſors. It commands the paſſage of the <hi>Elb;</hi> ſo that it highly concerns the <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgers</hi> to be at Peace with the King of <hi>Denmark.</hi> 2: <hi>Crempe,</hi> ſeated on a ſmall River of the ſame Name, and is one of the Keys of the Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> 3. <hi>Litzehoa.</hi> 4. <hi>Bredenbourg,</hi> one of the Neateſt little Towns in all the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Territories.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Holstein</hi> it ſelf, it taketh up the <hi>Inland</hi> parts between <hi>Stormar</hi> and <hi>Juitland</hi> ſave that it hath an Out-let into the <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick,</hi> on the <hi>South-VVest</hi> of <hi>VVagerland,</hi> the chief Towns are <hi>Kiel,</hi> ſeated upon a Navigable Arm of the <hi>Baltick.</hi> 2. <hi>Renſbourg</hi> the beſt fortified Town in the Dukedome. 3. <hi>VVilstor,</hi> a Neat and well Built City. 4. <hi>Niew-Munster,</hi> on the <hi>North-VVest</hi> of the
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:151645:41"/>Stor, and not far from the Head of it.</p>
            <p>And now for <hi>Juitland,</hi> it comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth all that part of the <hi>Cimbrick Cherſoneſe</hi> that is divided from the Dukedom of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtein,</hi> by the River <hi>Eyder,</hi> the Ancient boundary betwixt the <hi>Saxons</hi> and the <hi>Danes</hi> but principally by a long Trench and Wall from one Sea to the other, of ſuch bredth, that a Chariot, or two Horſemen a Breaſt, might Ride upon it. <hi>Godfrey</hi> King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> firſt Building this Trench in the time of <hi>Charlemain,</hi> or <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, in Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation of the <hi>Picts</hi> Wall in <hi>England,</hi> for hindring the Incurſions of the <hi>Saxons,</hi> or ſtopping the Carrier of the ſaid Emperours Victories. The Tract of this Wall being ſtill manifeſt to be ſeen, is call d <hi>Dennewark</hi> (or the <hi>Danes</hi> work) to this very day.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juitland</hi> was ſo called from the <hi>Juites,</hi> who, together with the <hi>Angli</hi> and Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring <hi>Saxons</hi> made a Conqueſt of the beſt part of <hi>Brittain.</hi> But the Ancient In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of this Province in the time of <hi>Prolomy</hi> and before, were the <hi>Cobandi, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Phunduſi, Charudes,</hi> and in the moſt <hi>Northern</hi> Tracts the <hi>Cimbri,</hi> of whom the four firſt were but Tribes or Nations Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that great expedition againſt <hi>Spain</hi> made by the <hi>Vandals</hi> on the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, the <hi>Juits</hi> and <hi>Angli</hi> though fit to Inlarge and
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:151645:41"/>ſhift their Habitations, each taking poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of ſuch quarters as lay neareſt to them; Thoſe <hi>Juites</hi> or <hi>Getae</hi> being a Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Scandia</hi> or <hi>Schonen,</hi> and there placed by <hi>Ptolomy;</hi> for he went up the <hi>Northern</hi> parts of the <hi>Cimbrick Charſoneſe,</hi> and gave it the Name of <hi>Juitland;</hi> the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther being a People of the <hi>Suevi,</hi> dwelling on the South of the <hi>Elb,</hi> poſſeſſed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves of thoſe parts which lay next their old Friends and Confederates the <hi>Saxons,</hi> their chief Town being <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> where <hi>Angelen,</hi> now an obſcure Village, but of great note in former times, doth preſerve their memory. Upon the <hi>Angli</hi>'s joyning with the <hi>Saxons</hi> in the Conqueſt of <hi>Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain,</hi> the <hi>Danes</hi> took that opportunity of Invading it in the abſence of the Natives; and having Conquered it as far as the River <hi>Eyder,</hi> they planted it with Colonies of their own Nation, and made it a part of that Kingdom.</p>
            <p>The Air of this Country is much more mild than that of the other Provinces of theſe <hi>Northern</hi> Parts, being temperated by the warm vapours of the Sea.</p>
            <p>The Soyl of <hi>Juitland</hi> is extremely rich, producing and affording all things neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary for the life of man. The Country being for the moſt part plain, little ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:151645:42"/>with Mountains, the Inhabitants reap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this double advantage from their Fields, in that they yield interchangeably both Fiſh and Corn; for, during one three years they plough the Land, and conſtantly reap the Fruits of it; and for the next three, let the Pools overflow the Land, to the end the Fiſh may eat up the Graſs (whom they catch as often as they pleaſe) and the Mud which is left behind enriches the Soyle.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juitland</hi> too aboundeth ſo in Cattle; that ſendeth yearly into <hi>Germany</hi> 50000 Oxen, beſides great ſtore of Butter, Cheeſe, Tallow, Hides, Horſes and Swine, having ſuch plenty of excellent Hams, that moſt of thoſe which paſs here in <hi>England</hi> under the name of <hi>Weſtphalia</hi>'s, come from thence. It hath all manner of Game Fowl, either for diverſion, neceſſaries, or luxury. It's Pools, Lakes and Rivers are furniſh'd with all ſorts of freſh Fiſh, eſpecially moſt excellent Salmons, and in great abundance. It's commodious Bays provide with plenty all ſorts of Foraign Commodities, as well as the Sea doth <hi>Whitings, Soles, Herrings, Mackeril, Pilchards, Oyſters, Smelts, Sprats, Shrimps, Lobſters, Crabs, Thornback, Rusfes, Muſcles, Prawns, Cockles, Conge, Turbots, Mades,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:151645:42"/>Scute, Eſcalops, Cod,</hi> &amp;c. Neither is it wanting of good Fruits. It has excellent Timber, both for building, for Shipping and for Firing. In ſhort, hardly any Country furniſhes more towards the neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, nay, and the amuzement, and the diverſions too of life, than this does.</p>
            <p>In regard of the Climate, it cannot be expected that its Vines ſhould come to any perfection, they being only to be ripened by the heat of the Sun; but its own Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities procure it the beſt Wines of all Countries, which nevertheleſs it does not ſtand in need of, it producing vaſt plenty and moſt excellent Barley, whereof they make their Ale and other Liquors, which if not more toothſome, yet perhaps more natural to their bodies and conſtitutions.</p>
            <p>It likewiſe Tranſports into other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries great Stores of <hi>Equipage for Shipping, Armors, Ox-hides, Buck-skins, Wainſcot, Fir-wood,</hi> and the like.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Juitland</hi> is divided into <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South,</hi> the latter containeth many conſiderable Towns; as firſt, <hi>Flensbourch,</hi> a deep, ſafe and commodious Port; <hi>Halem</hi> upon the <hi>German</hi> Ocean, near the mouth of the River <hi>Eyder; Itaderſleeve,</hi> a Biſhops See; <hi>Sondenberg,</hi> in the <hi>Peninſula,</hi> called <hi>Eyder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtede,</hi> over againſt the <hi>Strandt,</hi> an Iſland
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:151645:43"/>of the <hi>German</hi> Ocean; <hi>Sternberg,</hi> the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Reſidence of the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Governour <hi>Gottorp,</hi> a ſtrong Caſtle of the Duke of <hi>Slyvicks</hi> at the end of a large Inlet of the <hi>Baltick,</hi> remarkable for the Toll-Booth; at which Toll is paid one year with another for 50000 Oxen tranſported out of <hi>North Juitland</hi> into <hi>Germany; Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick</hi> the principal Town of this Province, an Epiſcopal See, and the Head of a Duke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Earl of <hi>Oldenburgh</hi> was choſen King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> the Dukedom of <hi>Holſtein</hi> became part of that Kingdom. Yet ſo that the Kings of <hi>Denmark</hi> were reckoned Princes of the Empire, as Dukes of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> tho not obliged to repair to any Dyet. Afterwards the title of Duke of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> with a conſiderable part of the Country, was given to <hi>Adolph Chriſtian</hi> the third brother, who Governed it inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changeably with his Brother by turns. Upon the deceaſe of this Duke and his Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue-Male; the title was conferred on <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lric</hi> King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth's Brother. Since his daies there have been ſeveral Houſes of the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein,</hi> as has been before ſhown; amongſt whom the Duke of <hi>Holſtein Gottorp</hi> is chief, and challenges the ſame power in governing and admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:151645:43"/>of Juſtice, as was at firſt conferred upon Duke <hi>Adolph,</hi> King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the 3's Brother. In the late Wars, the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> forced the preſent Duke of <hi>Got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torp</hi> to quit his Dukedom, and abandon all <hi>Holſtein</hi> to his Majeſties poſſeſſion. But at the ſigning of the Treaty between the Kings of <hi>France, Denmark</hi> and <hi>Sweden</hi> at <hi>Fontainbleu, Sept.</hi> 2. 1679. the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters promiſed their Maſter ſhould at the deſire of his moſt Chriſtian Majeſty, reſtore to the ſaid Duke all his Countrys, Towns and Places, in the ſame State they were at the ſigning of the Treaty, with all the Soveraignty that belonged to him, by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Treaties of <hi>Roſehild, Copenha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> and <hi>Weſtphalia.</hi> The Duke expected, beſides being reſtored to his Countries, ſome recompence for the damage his Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories had ſuffered during the War, by the vaſt ſums of Money which the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> had raiſed therein, as being one of the beſt Countries in all the <hi>North,</hi> or at leaſt to have had back the Cannon (being 100 excellent braſs pieces.) But his expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctations in this point were not anſwered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>North Juitland</hi> hath on the <hi>South</hi> the Dukedom of <hi>Sleſwick</hi> but ſurrounded by all other parts by the Sea, is divided into 4 Dioceſſes or <hi>Diſtricts:</hi> that of <hi>Rip</hi> or <hi>Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,</hi>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:151645:44"/>containing 30 Prefectures or <hi>Here</hi> (as they uſe to call them) ſeven Cities <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> walled Towns, and ten Caſtles.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That of <hi>Arhuſen</hi> lying on the <hi>North</hi> of <hi>Ripen,</hi> and more towards the <hi>Baltick</hi> containing 31 <hi>Herets</hi> or <hi>Prefectures,</hi> 7 Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties or walled Towns, 5 Caſtles, and the Iſlands of <hi>Sumſoe, Hiolim, Tuecen, Hiance<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Hilgenes</hi> and others.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That of <hi>Wiburg</hi> on the North of <hi>Arhuſen,</hi> containing 16 <hi>Herets,</hi> the Iſlands of <hi>Jegen.</hi> 2. <hi>Hanſholm.</hi> 3. <hi>Oſtholm.</hi> 4. <hi>Ciſland.</hi> 5. <hi>Egholm.</hi> 6. <hi>Bodum.</hi> Three Citys or walled Towns, and as many Caſtles, the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal whereof is <hi>Wiborch</hi> an Epiſcopal See; the ordinary ſeat of <hi>Judicature,</hi> for both the <hi>Juitlands.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That of <hi>Alburg</hi> or <hi>Vandalia,</hi> which is ſubdivided into four parts, as 1. <hi>Thyland,</hi> whoſe chief Town is <hi>Alborch</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Vandalia</hi>'s uſual Seat and Reſidence. 2. <hi>Morſce</hi> containing three <hi>Herets,</hi> the Town of <hi>Nicoping,</hi> the Caſtle of <hi>Lunſted,</hi> and the Iſle of <hi>Ageroe.</hi> 3. <hi>Hanheret</hi> containing four <hi>Herets,</hi> the Town of <hi>Thyſtad,</hi> a kind of Univerſity, the Caſtle of <hi>Orum,</hi> and the Iſlands of <hi>Oland</hi> and <hi>Oxholm.</hi> In this <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrict</hi> ſtandeth the Rock called <hi>Skaringclint,</hi> ſerving for a Sea Mark to prevent Mari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners running againſt the Quick-ſands which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:151645:44"/>lye about this Coaſt. 4. <hi>Wenſyſſel, Venſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia</hi> or <hi>Wenſlie</hi> containeth ſix <hi>Herets</hi> or <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectures.</hi> The Iſlands of <hi>Groſholm</hi> of <hi>Hertſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn,</hi> and <hi>Tideſholm,</hi> one Caſtle and three Towns; the moſt remarkable of which is <hi>Scagen,</hi> ſtanding at the utmoſt Promon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, or moſt Northerly Point of all this <hi>Cherſoneſe,</hi> being notorious for the Ship<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of many Ships of all Nations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zealand</hi> the largeſt, faireſt, and moſt fertil Iſland in the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea, lies <hi>Eaſt</hi> of <hi>Juitland,</hi> from which ſeparated by an arm of the Sea, called the <hi>Belt</hi> and <hi>Weſt</hi> of <hi>Schonen,</hi> from which it is parted by a freſh River not above a <hi>Dutch</hi> Mile in breadth, commonly called by the name of the <hi>Sund</hi> or <hi>Sound.</hi> This Iſland being about twelve <hi>German</hi> Miles broad, and eighteen long.</p>
            <p>It was anciently called <hi>Codanonia,</hi> which ſignifies the ſame thing as the modern words <hi>Danes</hi> or <hi>Denmark.</hi> Many of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Etymologiſts derive <hi>Seeland</hi> from <hi>Sordland</hi> or <hi>Seedland</hi> from the abundance of Corn which this Country affords. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers with greater Probability make the word ſignifie no more than an Iſland or parcel of Ground encompaſſed with the Sea.</p>
            <p>This Iſland containeth 15 Cities or Wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led Towns, the principal whereof are <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penhagen</hi>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:151645:45"/>(the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of this Iſland and of the whole Kingdom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> which is ſeated on the <hi>Eaſt Part</hi> of <hi>Zealand</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Sea ſhore. The <hi>Danes</hi> call it <hi>Kio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benhaun,</hi> and the <hi>Germans Copenharen,</hi> both which words are corruptions of <hi>Ki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obm inſhaven,</hi> or the <hi>Kaven of Merchants.</hi> The Town is of an Orbicular form, and very well fortified ſince the War in 1659. with the <hi>Swedes,</hi> having an <hi>Arcenal</hi> which perhaps excels any thing of that kind in <hi>Europe;</hi> In the <hi>Arcenal</hi> is kept a Coach with ſprings, by which means it goes as if it were of it ſelf, and of its own move<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; but the Artifice of this Work de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends on two men hidden under a cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Coach, of whom the one turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Wheels, which puſhed it on, and the other guided it by the means of a Rud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in the Head. Its Cathedral Church dedicated to St. <hi>Mary,</hi> is beautified with a noble Copper Spire, built at the charges of King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth. The <hi>Advow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſance</hi> of this Church belongs to the Profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors in the Univerſitie which was founded by <hi>Ericus</hi> the Ninth, but perfected by King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Firſt: by him and the ſucceeding Princes liberally endowed. The City is Governed by four Burgo-maſters, one whereof is Regent or Preſident for his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:151645:45"/>life. This Honour is conferred at preſent on that deſerving and learned Perſon <hi>P. John Reſenius</hi> Profeſſour of Moral Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy in the Univerſity at <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and Counſellour to the preſent King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark.</hi> Amongſt the Ornaments of the Town are the Market-place, which is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding ſpacious; the King's Palace all covered with Copper, ſtanding in an Iſland, wherein is kept a Ship of Ivory, wholly fitted, whereof the Tackling, Sails and Cannons were entirely of Ivory being an extraordinary fine piece of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufacture. The Obſervatory, or <hi>Runde Toorn</hi> which is very remarkable, and eſpecially for the faſhion of its Stair-caſe, if we may call it ſo, which is nothing but a Pavement which mount singeniouſly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Steps; and it is ſo very broad a Coach may eaſily go up to the top, and there too it has room enough to turn in. This Tower was built on purpoſe for the uſe of Aſtronomers, and out of it you go into a fine Library which ſtands on the ſide of the Tower. There is Marks of the Siege to be ſeen, which the <hi>Swedes</hi> laid to this City; amongſt others, a Bell made ſo full of holes by Cannon Bullets, that the King has thought fitting the marks thereof ſhould remain viſible by cauſing all the
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:151645:46"/>places that were pierced to be guilt. The <hi>Exchange</hi> is richly worth the ſeeing, and will merit a more ample Deſcription than this Compendium of the whole Kingdom will admit. The Citizens Houſes, till within theſe few years were very mean and low, moſt of them patcht up of Wood and Mortar; indeed the firſt riſe of this City was but very mean, for about the year 1168. <hi>Axil Wide</hi> ſirnamed <hi>Snare</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Denmark,</hi> built a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Fortification in this Iſland, wherein now ſtands the Caſtle. This was called after his Name <hi>Axel-huys;</hi> and was a good defence to the whole Iſland againſt the daily incurſions of Pyrats. Under the protection of this Fort ſeveral Fiſhermen, and others that Traded this way, uſed to Harbour their Ships in ſecurity; this cauſed a continual concourſe of the Natives, who reſorted hither to furniſh the Veſſels with ſuch Proviſions as their Country afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and in a ſhort time laid the firſt rude Draughts of a City, which at this day for Strength, Trade, Beauty and Bulk is not ſurpaſſed by many in <hi>Europe;</hi> for of late the Citizens are grown more curious, and experienced in Architecture, and few of their Streets are without a conſiderable number of ſtately brick Buildings. Its Haven alſo being one of the beſt in <hi>Europe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:151645:46"/>
               <hi>Amaga Amagri</hi> is <hi>Amagra</hi> or <hi>Ammak,</hi> is a ſmall Iſland on the Eaſt of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> about ſix <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in length and four in breadth; it abounds wonderfully in all manner of Fowl and Veniſon, has in it plenty of Corn, and furniſhes the Market at <hi>Copenhagen</hi> with weekly ſupplies of Milk, Butter, Cheeſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This Iſle of <hi>Ammak</hi> contains four or five Villages, and has two Pariſh Churches. But before we leave this Iſland, it will not perhaps be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful to relate an Encounter which hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened in it at the Siege of <hi>Copenhagen</hi> in 1660. which was ſo much the more conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable, becauſe both the <hi>Northern</hi> Kings were perſonally engaged in the action. The <hi>Swede</hi> obſerving that the <hi>Dane</hi> daily fetched Proviſions from the aforementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Iſle, the <hi>Ammak</hi> was reſolved to make a Deſcent in order to burn the Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, and deſtroy whatever might afford ſuſtenance or relief to the beſieged; for which purpoſe he put aboard about 1200 Foot, and 400 Horſe; and the King himſelf would needs be of the Party, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing ſo well done as where he was preſent, as well as naturally ambitious of ſharing perſonally in the glory of every brave action. Coming to the height of the <hi>Draker,</hi> he forced his Landing upon
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:151645:47"/>the Point of the Iſle, and conſtrained them upon the Guard to abandon their Poſt. He marches up the Iſle, and deſtroys all before him; and the <hi>Danes</hi> fearing he came to fortifie ſome Poſt on that ſide, ſet fire to the Village next adjacent to the Town, as the <hi>Swede</hi> had done to the reſt. Having done this work, the <hi>Swede</hi> retreats to his Boats too ſecurely: ſome ſcattered from the Body, others encumbred with Plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Mean while the <hi>Daniſh</hi> King Sallies out in perſon with three hundred Horſe, and two hundred Dragoons, beſides ſome few Commanded Foot mounted behind, falls in upon the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Rear, flew ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of them, and put the reſt in diſorder. The <hi>Swediſh</hi> King mounted upon an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly Horſe, bounding and curveting with him, ran great hazard of falling that day into the <hi>Daniſh</hi> hands. But the <hi>Dane</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not knowing all his advantages, or not willing to be drawn too far from his Town, by an over eager preſſing upon an Enemy who out numbred him, ſounded a ſeaſonable retreat.</p>
            <p>The next place of Note is <hi>Roſchild,</hi> which takes its name from a River run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by the Town, which drives <hi>ſcaven</hi> Mills; It was formerly the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the whole Kingdom, fortified with a Wall,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:151645:47"/>Ditch and Bulwark, and contained no leſs than 27 fair Churches. This Town was made a Biſhop's See by <hi>Suenotho</hi> King of <hi>England, Denmark, Sweden</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> about the year 1012. who gave the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Roſchild</hi> (which is now ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed up by <hi>Copenhagen</hi>) to <hi>Gerebrand</hi> a Monk. In the Cathedral Church of this Town, are to be ſeen very fair and ſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Tombs of many of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Elſeneur,</hi> the chief Ornament and Strength of which Town lies in <hi>Cronen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> is ſeated on that neck of the Sea cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Oriſundt</hi> or the <hi>Sound,</hi> which parts <hi>Sealand</hi> from <hi>Schonen. Cronenburgh</hi> is built of hewn Free-ſtone, brought hither out of <hi>Scotland,</hi> and this undertaken with incredible pains and charge by King <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drick</hi> the Second, without a penny Subſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy from the Subjects, tho he covered it with Coper; the Foundation of it being laid on huge Stone ſunk into the Sea, and ſo faſtened together, that no Storm or Tempeſt, how violent ſoever, is able to ſhake it; well fortified as well as founded, and mixt of a Palace and of a Fort, having for many years been the Seat of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings, who had from hence one of the moſt pleaſant and profitable proſpects of the whole Kingdom: every Ship that
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:151645:48"/>paſſes this Streight, being obliged to ſtrike Sail to <hi>Croneburg;</hi> and that done, the Maſter is to come to a Compoſition in the City for Cuſtom, upon the pain of the Confiſcation and Loading.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fredericksberg</hi> ſeated amongſt pleaſant Woods of Beech, and about the middle way between <hi>Elſeneur</hi> and <hi>Copenhagen;</hi> this Fabrick was firſt began by one <hi>Harlef</hi> a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Nobleman, who ſold it to King <hi>Fredrick</hi> the Second, who fell upon en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larging and beautifying it to a high de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. After this King's death, his Son <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth ſpared no charges in compleating what his Father left unfiniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, adorning it with the richeſt Pictures, Statues, Hangings, the Locks and bars in the Windows being all of beaten Silver, ſo as it not only ſurpaſſes all that is in the North: but the World can hardly para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel this piece. The adjoyning Park has amongſt other Foreign Beaſts a Stock of Foreign Deer tranſported hither out of <hi>England</hi> in the 24 of Q. <hi>Eliz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ringſtede,</hi> a Town of the greateſt Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity of any except <hi>Roſchild</hi> in <hi>Denmark;</hi> many of the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Kings lying buried in the place, particularly King <hi>Waldemar</hi> the Firſt, and <hi>Eric</hi> the Godly; its ſcituation being in the very Center of the Land; its
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:151645:48"/>want of Trade, makes it daily decay.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sora</hi> of old being beautified with a goodly Monaſtery, the Revenues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, at the alteration of Religion, were converted to the maintenance of a Free-School built here by <hi>Fredrick</hi> the Firſt. But in the year 1623. <hi>Chriſtiern</hi> the fourth adding hereunto the Revenues of two other diſſolved Monaſteries, the one of the Iſle of <hi>Laland,</hi> and the other in <hi>Juitland,</hi> founded here a new Univerſity for the maintenance of ſeveral learned men, who were to be employed in writing and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing the Hiſtory of the Acts and Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Kings, and other Heroes, of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and for the better ſupply of Learned Miniſters for the Churches of <hi>Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> (which before could not be provided for out of <hi>Copenhagen,</hi> and furniſhed it with men of eminence in all Arts and Sciences for its firſt Profeſſors. Beſides, he annexed an Academy with fit Maſters, to teach perfectly all Gentile and Marſhal Exerciſes, as Dancing, Vault<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Riding the Great Horſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anderskaw</hi> or <hi>Anderſhauw,</hi> formerly a great Monaſtery, now a ſtrong Caſtle about an <hi>Engliſh</hi> Mile from <hi>Slagen.</hi> It is is ſeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in a level Champaign Country, and delicately well built.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="88" facs="tcp:151645:49"/>
               <hi>Kallenburg</hi> was formerly a ſmall Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage inhabited by none but Fiſher-men, but about the year 1158. or I as ſome, 117. it was turned into a City, and beautified with a Caſtle, Church and ſeveral other publick Buildings. 'Tis at preſent a Town of good Trade, having the conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nience of as ſafe an Harbour for Ships as any Haven in <hi>Denmark.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Korſor,</hi> ſo called from the Multitude of Croſſes erected formerly in the places out of the abundance of ſuperſtitious zeal in the Inhabitants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Koge,</hi> a ſmall but very rich and popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous City; about ſixteen <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles from <hi>Copenhagen.</hi> It is a place much thronged with Corn Merchants, and Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongers, driving a conſiderable Trade, and being in a pleaſant ſituation.</p>
            <div type="region">
               <head>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>NEN.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>F<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nen</hi> is Situated betwixt <hi>Seeland</hi> and <hi>Juitland,</hi> from which laſt it is parted by a Straight, called <hi>Middlefar-ſundt,</hi> about one <hi>German</hi> Mile in breadth, and ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Seeland</hi> by the <hi>Beltis ſundt,</hi> or <hi>Baltick Bay,</hi> which is ſo narrow and ſmall a Frith, that the Iſland and the <hi>Cherſoneſe</hi> ſeem joyned together.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:151645:49"/>
The length of this Iſland from Eaſt to Weſt is Ten <hi>German</hi> Miles, and the breadth Eight: It is looked upon as the Pleaſanteſt piece of Ground in the King of <hi>Denmark</hi>'s Dominions; abounding beſides with all manner of Corn, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Wheat and Rye, which is hence Yearly Tranſported in great Quantities unto other Nations. Beſides, the Natives have generally great Herds of Cattel, and good Breeds of Horſes. The Woods, which overſpread almoſt the whole Iſland, are exceeding well ſtored with Deer, Hares, and Foxes. This Iſland contains Four and Twenty <hi>Herets</hi> or <hi>Prefectures,</hi> Sixteen Towns, and Six Royal Caſtles, beſides many goodly Villages and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemens Houſes.</p>
               <p>The Chief City of <hi>Funen</hi> is <hi>Ottenſee,</hi> ſeated in the very center of the Iſland, and therefore a fit place for the Seſſions of the Nobility and Magiſtracy, which are Yearly held in this place; as were like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the General Aſſemblies of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Denmark,</hi> before the Year 1660. The Buildings in this Town are generally well Built, and the Streets Uniform. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other Publick Structures, there are in it two fair Churches, whereof one is Dedicated to St. <hi>Cnuts,</hi> the other to St.
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:151645:50"/>
                  <hi>Francis.</hi> Not far from the former of theſe ſtands a ſtately Town Hall upon a very ſpacious Market-place, where King <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drick</hi> the Second renewed the Ancient League between the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> and the Dukes of <hi>Holſtein</hi> and <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> in the Year 1575. When the Quires of St. <hi>Cnut</hi>'s Church was Repaired in the Year 1582, the Work men found in a Vaulta Copper Coffin, gilded and adorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Precious Stones, upon which was writ the following Inſcription in Old <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine-Gothic</hi> Characters.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Jam Coelo tutus ſummo cum Rege <hi>Canutus</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Martyr in aurata Rex atque reconditur arca:</l>
                  <l>Et pro juſtitiae factis occiſus inique;</l>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Chriſtum vitae ſic morte fatetur in ipſa.</l>
                  <l>Traditur a proprio ſicut Deus ipſe, Miniſtro.</l>
                  <date>
                     <hi>A. D. MLXXXVI.</hi>
                  </date>
               </q>
               <p>Other Towns of Note in <hi>Funen,</hi> are, 1. <hi>Bowens,</hi> a Port Town of good Trade on the Weſt ſide of the Iſland, at the North end of <hi>Medelfar ſund.</hi> 2. <hi>Middlefar,</hi> ſeated on the Common Paſſage from this Iſland to <hi>Kolding</hi> in <hi>Juitland.</hi> On the thirteenth of <hi>January,</hi> in the Year 1658, <hi>Carolus Guſtavus,</hi> King of <hi>Sweden,</hi> led his Army over the Ice to this place, and having
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:151645:50"/>Routed the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Forces which Oppoſed him, made himſelf Maſter of the whole Iſland of <hi>Funen.</hi> 3. <hi>Aſcens,</hi> not far from the Mountains of <hi>Oſſenburg,</hi> memorable only for a Victory gained near it by <hi>John Rantzaw,</hi> King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Third's Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, who levelled the City to the ground. 4. <hi>Foborg,</hi> upon the Southern Coaſt of the Iſland: It was once Burnt by the unruly Souldiers of <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Third, whilſt <hi>Odenſee</hi> (adhering to the Captive Prince, <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Second, who at that time was kept cloſe Priſoner at <hi>Sunderburg</hi>) Redeem'd it ſelf from the like Fate by a large Sum of Money. 5. <hi>Swynburg,</hi> over againſt the Iſle of <hi>Langland;</hi> from this place <hi>Carolus Guſtavus</hi> led his Army over the Ice into <hi>Seeland</hi> in the Year 1658. 6. <hi>Nyburg,</hi> the uſual Paſſage from <hi>Funen</hi> into <hi>Seeland.</hi> This City was firſt Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with a Moat and Bullwarks by King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Third: It is very Memorable for the Battel fought by the Confederates of the Empire, <hi>Brandenburgh, Poland,</hi> and the <hi>Low Countries,</hi> in the Year 1659. againſt the <hi>Swedes,</hi> who were beaten in that Rencounter, and utterly Routed out of <hi>Schonen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Funen</hi> there are reckoned up no leſs than Two Hundred Sixty four Pariſh Churches.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:151645:51"/>
               <head>ZALAND.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LAland,</hi> or <hi>Lawland,</hi> ſo called from its low Situation, is disjoyned from <hi>Seeland</hi> by a little narrow Straight, called <hi>Groneſendt,</hi> and is about Thirty two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in length, and two in breadth. This is a very Fruitful Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, hath good ſtore of Rich Paſturage, and affords ſuch great Plenty of Corn and Cheſnuts, that Ships full Freighted with them are ſent Yearly hence.</p>
               <p>It contains four <hi>Herets</hi> or Lordſhips, and as many Cities. The great Towns or Cities are, 1. <hi>Naſchaw,</hi> or <hi>Naſhſcouw;</hi> which (together with the adjoyning Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery) was Stormed, Taken, and Burnt by the <hi>Lubeckers</hi> in the Year 1510. 2. <hi>Saſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coping.</hi> 3. <hi>Newſtadt,</hi> once Famous for a Noble Monaſtery Built there <hi>A. D.</hi> 1286. 4. <hi>Lavingſcoping.</hi> Beſides theſe, the Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nery of <hi>Marioebo</hi> or <hi>Mariboane,</hi> was as Conſiderable and Remarkable a Place as any in the whole Iſland.</p>
               <p>The other Iſlands in the <hi>Baltique</hi> now belonging to the <hi>Dane,</hi> worth the taking Notice of, are,</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:151645:51"/>
1. <hi>Falſter,</hi> a conſiderable Iſland, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyning to <hi>Laland.</hi> It is not above Six<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in length, but affords Plenty of Corn Yearly to ſome Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Iſlands, and to the very Conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. The Principal Towns of this Iſle are,
<list>
                     <item>1. <hi>Nicoping,</hi> which, for the Elegancy of the Place, and the Pleaſantneſs of the Situation, is by Dr. <hi>Heylin</hi> ſtyled, <hi>The NAPLES of Denmark.</hi> 2. <hi>Stubcopen,</hi> or <hi>Stabcoping,</hi> has ſome Trade upon the Account of its being the Ordinary Paſſage between <hi>Seeland</hi> and <hi>Germany.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Langeland,</hi> a narrow Iſland betwixt <hi>Funen</hi> and <hi>Laland,</hi> ſeven <hi>Dutch</hi> Miles in length; in which, beſides many Villages and Gentlemens Houſes, and ſixteen Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Churches, is the Town of <hi>Rudcoping,</hi> and the Impregnable Caſtle of <hi>Traneker,</hi> which is admirably well provided with all manner of Military Ammunition.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>Mona,</hi> or <hi>Meun,</hi> a Chalky Iſland to the North-Eaſt of <hi>Falſter:</hi> It ſerves for a good Land-mark to the <hi>German</hi> Veſſels that Trade in thoſe Seas. The only Town of Conſequence in it is <hi>Stege,</hi> which bravely withſtood the <hi>Lubeckers</hi> in the Year 1510, and forced them at laſt to Retreat.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="94" facs="tcp:151645:52"/>
4. <hi>Alſen,</hi> another little Iſland, called in <hi>Latin, Elyſia,</hi> oppoſite to the Gulph or Bay of <hi>Flensburg,</hi> in the Dukedom of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> of which it is a part, and therefore only Subject to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark</hi> as Dukes of <hi>Sleſwick.</hi> Some <hi>Daniſh</hi> Antiquaries do think the <hi>Eleſii, Arii,</hi> and <hi>Manimi,</hi> mentioned by <hi>Tacitus,</hi> were the Ancient Inhabitants of this Iſland <hi>Ar</hi> and <hi>Meun;</hi> and that theſe three Iſles have the ſame Names at this day (with ſome ſmall alteration) which they had when <hi>Tacitus</hi> writ his Annals. It is well ſtored with Beaſts for Profit, and Game for Pleaſure; and ſo Populous, that ſeveral Thouſands of ſtout Fighting Men have been Raiſed in a very ſhort time out of its four Towns and Thirteen Pariſhes. The Principal place of the Iſland, is the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Sunderburg,</hi> was heretofore one of the Ordinary Reſidences of the Dukes of <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> and Honoured with the Birth of many of their Princes of the Royal Family, and is at this day one of the ſtrongeſt Holds which the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> ſtands poſſeſſed of.</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Femeren,</hi> or <hi>Fimbriu,</hi> is a ſmall Iſland on the Coaſt of <hi>Wagerland,</hi> from which it is ſeparated by a very narrow Channel. This Plot of Ground has ever
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:151645:52"/>been look'd upon as one of the moſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable Keys of <hi>Denmark.</hi> This Crown thinking it of that Importance; as to ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the <hi>Germans</hi> to run over all <hi>Holſtein,</hi> and both <hi>Juitlands,</hi> rather than they ſhould poſſeſs themſelves of this Iſle. And therefore in the Year 1628, King <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth took care to put ſtrong Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons into every place of Moment in it, and to Fortifie the Old Caſtles and Towns which his Predeceſſors had ſuffered to decay and ſlighted. Towns of any Note in it, are <hi>Derborch, Stabul,</hi> and <hi>Pitterſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorp.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Hucen,</hi> or <hi>Wcen,</hi> commonly called by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> the Scarlet Iſland, as is ſaid upon the account of a Bargain between Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark,</hi> ſhe being to have the Iſland for as much Scarlet Cloth as would cover it. In this Iſland did <hi>Tycho Brache,</hi> a <hi>Daniſh</hi> Noble-Man, make moſt of his Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Obſervations in Aſtronomy. King <hi>Frederick</hi> the Second giving him it as a place remote from all Troubles, and fit for a Students Retirement. Here <hi>Tycho</hi> about the Year 1575 Built his <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>raniburg,</hi> (an Obſervatory Built like a Caſtle, and Fenced round with Regular Fortifications) which he Adorned with a Collection of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:151645:53"/>the moſt exact Mathematical Inſtruments that could poſſibly be made or procured. This <hi>Tycho,</hi> amongſt other his Admirers, had the Honour of a Viſit from King <hi>James,</hi> in his return from the Conſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of his Marriage with Queen <hi>Ann.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>As for the other little inconſiderable Iſlands, they are not worth the trouble of Deſcribing, nor of the Readers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration. Wherefore we will paſs on to the Kingdom of <hi>Norway.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:151645:53"/>
               <head>NORWAY.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NORWAY</hi> is bounded in the <hi>South</hi> with the <hi>Baltick</hi> Straits, which ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate it from <hi>Juitland;</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Poland</hi> and <hi>Sweden,</hi> from which it is parted by a perpetual Ridge of rough and wild Mountains, called the <hi>Dofrine</hi> Hills; in the North and Weſt with the <hi>Northern</hi> Ocean: the whole length of it, from the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea as far as <hi>Finmark,</hi> is reckoned to be about Eight hundred and forty <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles.</p>
               <p>As for the Derivation of its Name <hi>Norway</hi> (or <hi>Norweg</hi> as the <hi>Germans</hi> write it; whence the Latin word <hi>Norwegia</hi>) is only <hi>Via ſeutractus ſeptentrionalis;</hi> i.e. A Countrey ſcituated towards the North. Hence in the <hi>Daniſh, Swediſh,</hi> and <hi>Norwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gian</hi> Tongues, 'tis to this day called <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rike,</hi> or the <hi>Northern</hi> Kingdom; and we find that anciently all the Northern Kingdoms were called <hi>Regna Norica.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for its Poſition, in regard of the Heavens, it reacheth from the firſt Parallel, of the Twelfth Clime, where the Pole is elevated 58 Degrees, 20 Minutes, as far as to 71 of Latitude, by which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the longeſt day in the <hi>Southern</hi>
                  <pb n="100" facs="tcp:151645:54"/>Point is but 10 Hours: Whereas at <hi>Ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buy</hi>'s, being ſituate fartheſt <hi>North</hi> of all this Countrey, they have no Night for almoſt Three Months together.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Part of <hi>Norway</hi> is very thinly inhabited, being a Country of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but inacceſſible Craggy Mountains; towards the <hi>South</hi> it is better peopled, the Inhabitants dwelling in pleaſant Val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys incircled with delightful Hills; the reſt of the Countrey is over-ſpread with Woods, which afford moſt part of <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope</hi> Deal Boards and Maſts for Ships.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Dofrine</hi> Hills which divide this Realm from <hi>Sweden,</hi> are perpetually co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with Snow; and ſend down in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable bitter Winds into the Valleys beneath, which renders 'em deſolate and unfruitful. But the Air of the more <hi>Weſtern</hi> Coaſts of this Kingdom is much more milder and temperate, and would be healthful too, were not the Countrey troubled with certain little Beaſts which they call <hi>Lemmers:</hi> they are about the the bigneſs of a Field-Mouſe, and are by the Inhabitants ſaid to drop out of the Clouds in bad Weather; they devour like the Locuſt every green thing on the Earth; and at a certain time die all in heaps (as it were) together, and with their ſtench and putrefaction ſo poiſonthe Air, that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:151645:54"/>the poor people are long after troubled with the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> and a Giddineſs in the Head, which is moſt eſpecially apt to ſeize on Strangers unacquainted with the danger, and unprepared againſt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtemper: But the <hi>Lemmers</hi> do not more frequently infeſt the Land, than the <hi>Whales</hi> do terrifie and moleſt the Sho res; yet the Mariners and Inhabitants of the Sea-Coaſts have found out a Remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Violence and Fury, for they mingle ſome Water with the Oyl of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor,</hi> the ſmell whereof doth force 'em to retire immediately; had not this help and expedient been found out, there would be no Fiſhing upon the Coaſts of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way:</hi> which with Materials for Shipping is the greateſt ſtaple Commodity of the Country.</p>
               <p>Their Valleys are well ſtock'd with good Breeds of Cattle, which enable the Inhabitants to Export every year great abundance of Butter, Tallow, Hides, and Cheeſe; Barley is their chief Grain. Their Woods furniſh Timber, Pitch, Tar, Rich Furs, and vaſt plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Filbirds:</hi> They alſo drive a great Trade with their <hi>Train-Oyl</hi> and <hi>Stock Fiſh,</hi> which is vended over all <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the Year 1623. <hi>Chriſtian</hi> the Fourth King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> put ſeveral Artiſts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:151645:55"/>the ſearch of ſome <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver Mines,</hi> and they are ſaid to have found ſome Lumps of the Ore of both thoſe <hi>Metals,</hi> which they Preſented to that Prince. But whether the Ores lying ſo deep, it would not quit Coſts, or that the thinneſs or ignorance of the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants, in refining of Minerals themſelves, with their jealouſie and unwillingneſs to admit any Forreigners skill'd in that way into their Countrey; this Diicovery ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver turned to any conſiderable Account.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Norwegians</hi> jump much with the <hi>Danes</hi> in their Complexion and Humour, but are generally more effeminate and lazy; yet not naturally ſo, but thro want of Employment and Exerciſe. The Policy of the Crown of <hi>Denmark</hi> not thinking fit to employ this Nation in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Wars, for fear of enuring 'em, and making them expert in <hi>Arms.</hi> And thro this Umbrage, takes <hi>all</hi> the Courſes im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aginable to Cow and diſpirit them. Now tho the ancient <hi>Norwegians</hi> are ſaid to have been notorious Pyrats; yet at this day hardly any Seas are leſs infeſted with Pyracy than thoſe of <hi>Norway.</hi> Not that the Modern Inhabitants are bleſt with more Honeſty than their Anceſtors, but the <hi>Daniſh</hi> ſway is ſo rigorous, as not to allow them any Shipping, nor
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:151645:55"/>any other means to pamper, grow reſty, and head ſtrong, but on the contrary fleeces, ſqueezes, and keeps them in the loweſt ſervitude.</p>
               <p>Their Diet is what they Export to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Countreys, principally Stock Fiſh, and a courſe kind of Butter and Cheeſe, Their uſual Drink <hi>Roſtock</hi> Ale, their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner being commonly to drink three Draughts; one in remembrance of God, the ſecond to the Kings Health, and the third to the Queens.</p>
               <p>As the Towns in <hi>Norway</hi> are very thin, ſo the Buildings for the moſt part are very poor and miſerable; generally patched up of dirt and hurdles, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what reſembling our Cotrage Houſes in the Fen Countreys.</p>
               <p>As for the Government of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, it is ſtill reckoned a diſtinct King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom from that of <hi>Denmark;</hi> and had formerly Independant Kings of its own, who ſometimes domineer'd over the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Kings of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Denmark.</hi> But the laſt King of the <hi>Norwegian</hi> Race, who Reigned in their Kingdom, was <hi>Haguin;</hi> who in the year 1363 Married <hi>Margaret</hi> Eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Waldemar</hi> the third, King of <hi>Denmark,</hi> and ſo united the two Crowns. Now tho this King had only one Son by Queen <hi>Margaret,</hi> who died
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:151645:56"/>without Iſſue, yet the <hi>Danes</hi> having once got footing in, and poſſeſſion of this Kingdom, were reſolved not to abandon ſuch an advantage, nor part from their Station; and to ſecure it, immediately clapt ſtrong Garriſons into all the Cities and Fortreſſes of moment in the Nation. For the better Management of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, it is divided into five Prefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures anſwerable to the five Caſtles which command them.</p>
               <p>Now 1. The Prefecture of <hi>Maſterland</hi> or <hi>Maeſtrandt</hi> is ſituated moſt towards the South, and is commanded by the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle of <hi>Bahuy's,</hi> now in the hands of the King of <hi>Sweden.</hi> That <hi>Caſtle</hi> was firſt Built by <hi>Haguin</hi> the IV. King of <hi>Norway,</hi> about the year 1309, upon a ſteep Rock on the Bank of the River <hi>Srollet,</hi> and then eſteem'd the beſt Fort the King had in his Dominions; and a ſufficient Barrier againſt the frequent Attacks and Inroads of the <hi>Swedes</hi> and <hi>Weſtro-Goths:</hi> Beſides the <hi>City</hi> of <hi>Maeſtrandt</hi> noted for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite quantity of Herrings caught there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>about, there's two more of leſs note, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal</hi> and <hi>Oldawalt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The 2. Prefecture contains the Biſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pricks of <hi>Anſlo</hi> and <hi>Staffenger,</hi> with the Province of <hi>Aggerhuys,</hi> having under its Command, firſt the Towns of <hi>Anſlo, Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlo,</hi>
                  <pb n="105" facs="tcp:151645:56"/>or <hi>Aſloia,</hi> poſſeſſ of moſt repute, as being an Epiſcopal See, and the place where the Courts of Judicature are kept for all <hi>Norway.</hi> All Cauſes and Suits at Law being heard and determined before the Governour, who acts as <hi>Vice Roy</hi> of the Kingdom. The Cathedral of this Town is dedicated to <hi>Alward,</hi> who took great pains to Convert the <hi>Norwegian Pagans.</hi> This Church has to ſhow the Sword of <hi>Haquin,</hi> one of their moſt Primitive Kings, being a ſignal Inſtance and Proof of the Strength and admirable Art of ſome <hi>Norwegians</hi> of former Ages. The Hilt of it is made of Chryſtal curiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly wrought and poliſhed; whence ſome have inferred that the uſe of Chryſtal was anciently much more ordinary in <hi>Norway,</hi> than it is at this day in any part of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Not far from <hi>Opſlo</hi> on the oppoſite ſide of the <hi>Bay</hi> ſtands the Caſtle of <hi>Aggerhuyſen;</hi> famous for the brave reſiſtance it made the <hi>Swediſh</hi> Army in the Year 1567, which laid a cloſe and brisk Seige to it for Eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen Weeks together; but was at laſt beat off and forced to a ſhameful Retreat. <hi>Tons<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg</hi> formerly a place of Retreat of the Kings of <hi>Norway, Hammer</hi> in former times a Biſhops See, but now united to that of <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlo.</hi> Some Authors do affirm that near unto <hi>Hammer</hi> a huge and monſtrous Serpent
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:151645:57"/>doth conſtantly appear before any great Change in the State or Government of the Kingdom of <hi>Norway. Saltzburg, Frederik<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtadt</hi> and <hi>Scheene,</hi> driving all a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Trade from the <hi>Copper</hi> and <hi>Iron Mines,</hi> which abound more hereabouts than in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other part of the Kingdom. In this Province were the <hi>Silver Mines</hi> above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned firſt diſcovered, and ſome of the adjoyning Hills, are by the Neighbour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood to this day called <hi>Silver Bergen,</hi> or <hi>the Mountains of Silver.</hi> Now <hi>Norway</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted for the greateſt part, if not all its Trade, to thoſe Mines, and the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Woods of Fir and Pinetrees which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſpread this part of the Country.</p>
               <p>The City of <hi>Staffenger</hi> lies in 59 deg. (ſome reckon 60, and a great many odd min.) of Latitude, being ſeated upon a <hi>Demy-Iſland</hi> upon a great <hi>Bay</hi> of the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern Ocean,</hi> full of ſmall <hi>Iſlands,</hi> and guard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the ſtrong <hi>Caſtle</hi> of <hi>Doeswick,</hi> which ſtands about two <hi>Engliſh Miles</hi> from the Town; this City is a Biſhops See, and is divided into ſeveral Diſtricts, tho in civil Affairs it is under the Juriſdiction of the Governour of <hi>Aggerhuyſen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beyond the <hi>Bay</hi> is ſeen the Iſland <hi>Schute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes,</hi> Twelve <hi>Engliſh Miles</hi> in length, but ſcarce two in breadth: This Iſland con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains ſeveral Villages, and between it and
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:151645:57"/>the Continent runs a narrow Frith to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen,</hi> which the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants call the <hi>Liedt van Berghen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Province of <hi>Tillemarch</hi> or <hi>Thyle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>march,</hi> appertaineth to the Biſhoprick of <hi>Staffenger.</hi> The Pariſh or <hi>Hollen,</hi> in this Pariſh is very remarkable for a Church-Yard or Burying Place, on the top of a Church, Dedicated to St. <hi>Michael,</hi> which is cut out of a great high Rock, called by the Neighbourhood <hi>Vear,</hi> upon the Lake <hi>Nordſce,</hi> half a Mile diſtant from <hi>Scheen;</hi> 'tis thought by ſome to have been former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la a <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> Temple, but converted to <hi>Chriſtian</hi> uſes upon the firſt planting of the Goſpel in this Kingdom.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bergenhuis</hi> is the third Caſtle of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in <hi>Norway:</hi> This Prefecture and Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick, being the moſt fruitful and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant part of all <hi>Norway,</hi> lying in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle or heart of the Kingdom, to the North of <hi>Aggerhuyſen.</hi> It has its Name from the Stately and Noble Mart Town of <hi>Berghen;</hi> or elſe from the ſtrong Caſtle of <hi>Bergenhuyſen,</hi> the uſual Seat of the <hi>Vice-Roy</hi> of <hi>Norway,</hi> at a ſmall diſtance to the North of <hi>Berghen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Berghen</hi> is the Granary and Magazine of the whole Kingdom of <hi>Norway,</hi> for <hi>Bahuys,</hi> it is diſtant about Fourty hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles by Sea, and Two hundred
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:151645:58"/>and forty by Land; from <hi>Trunthein</hi> as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny; from <hi>Scagen,</hi> the outmoſt Promon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory of <hi>Juis Iſland,</hi> almoſt Three hundred and twenty. Some <hi>Etymologiſts</hi> have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived its Name from the <hi>Norwegian</hi> Verb <hi>Berghen,</hi> which ſignifies to hide or conceal; becauſe the Haven being ſurrounded with Hills, ſeems to be a kind of Sculking place for Ships, where Veſſels of <hi>Two hundred Tun</hi> and upwards, ride in a ſpacious and moſt ſecure Harbour, free from any danger of Wind and Weather. But the true deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the word is this, <hi>Berghen</hi> in the <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wegian Tongues</hi> alſo ſignifies Mountains, and <hi>Bergenhuyſen</hi> a Company of Houſes among the Hills. The Buildings of this <hi>Town</hi> till of late were but very mean and deſpiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, for the moſt part of Wood covered with <hi>green Turf,</hi> and ſo often burnt down. But the Forreigners that have traded thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, within theſe few years have adorn'd the Town with an Exchange, and many goodly private Houſes; the principal <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity</hi> which <hi>Berghen</hi> Trades in, is <hi>Stock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſh,</hi> which they catch upon thoſe Coaſts in Winter, commonly in <hi>January,</hi> for the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniency of drying it in the cold and ſharp <hi>Air,</hi> beſides all ſorts of <hi>Furrs,</hi> and vaſt quantities of <hi>dried Fiſh, Butter, Tallow, Hides,</hi> &amp;c. are brought hither from all parts of <hi>Norway</hi> to be Imported into For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:151645:58"/>
The Governour of <hi>Berghen</hi> has under his Juriſdiction the Prefectures of <hi>Leehorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leen, Nordhornleen, Soghue, Sudfiord Nord,</hi> and <hi>Sundmerleen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Prefecture and Biſhoprick of <hi>Trun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thein</hi> is reckoned the fourth Government in <hi>Norway,</hi> and its <hi>City</hi> anciently called <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>droſia,</hi> was formerly the <hi>Metropolis</hi> of the whole Kingdom, &amp; the Seat of the <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Archbiſhop</hi> of <hi>Norway.</hi> It was in former times a beautiful City, but being burnt down in the year 1522, and kept in ſuch ſubjection and oppreſſion by the <hi>Danes,</hi> it has been ſo far from being able to receive its primitive Splendor, that it ſeems more like a <hi>Village</hi> than a <hi>City.</hi> Yet ſomething of the ancient <hi>Grandeur</hi> ſtill appears in the <hi>Cathedral</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to St. <hi>Ilaus,</hi> which (though almoſt conſumed by <hi>Fire</hi>) by the <hi>Ruins,</hi> ſhews it ſelf to have been one of the moſt <hi>Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> and <hi>largeſt Fabricks</hi> in the <hi>World.</hi> In this <hi>Church</hi> the <hi>Huntſmen</hi> were wont to make a yearly <hi>Offering</hi> of the Skins of the largeſt and ſtouteſt <hi>White Bears</hi> which they kill'd, for the <hi>Prieſts</hi> to tread upon at <hi>Divine Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. Greenland</hi> and <hi>Iſeland,</hi> were formerly Diſtricts of the Dioceſs of <hi>Truntheim,</hi> but this Biſhoprick is now confined within nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower bounds: Moſt part of this Country having no Wood at all growing in it, make
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:151645:59"/>uſe of <hi>Fiſh bones</hi> for Fuel, for Timber to build their Houſes, and for ſeveral <hi>Imple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of <hi>Houſhold Stuff:</hi> And with the <hi>fat</hi> of thoſe ſame <hi>fiſh</hi> they <hi>feed</hi> their <hi>Lamps</hi> in <hi>Winter.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The fifth and laſt Prefecture command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Countrey, is that of <hi>Wardhuyſe,</hi> its Caſtle has its Name from the <hi>Iſland Warda</hi> wherein it ſtands, and is about Eight <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> Miles from the main Land of <hi>Finmark,</hi> and near Twelve in Compaſs; the Food of the Inhabitants of this and the Neighbou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring <hi>Iſland</hi> is only <hi>Stock-Fiſh,</hi> which they dry in the Froſt. No manner of Bread nor Drink have they, but what is Imported from Forreign Countreys; ſome Cattle they have, yet none but ſuch as can live on dry'd Fiſh their Maſters Diet. The Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor retires in the <hi>Winter</hi> more <hi>Southerly</hi> within the <hi>Land,</hi> by reaſon of the extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity of the <hi>Cold,</hi> and the long abſence of the <hi>Sun</hi> for ſome Months together, the Town lying within the <hi>Artick Circle.</hi> It is much improved of late, ſince the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moval of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Trading from <hi>Novo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grod</hi> to St. <hi>Nicholas,</hi> not far from hence, and is both profitable and uſeful to the <hi>Crown</hi> of <hi>Denmark</hi> in regard of its ſtrength, the <hi>Dutch</hi> and <hi>Engliſh</hi> being obliged to touch at it in their way to <hi>Moſcovy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>On the North of <hi>Norway</hi> lies <hi>Finmark,</hi> or
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:151645:59"/>as the Natives call it, <hi>Taakemark,</hi> which is not divided as all other Countries gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally are, into diſtinct Lordſhips and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritances, but every Man pretends a Right and Title to every part of the Land, and the ſtrength of the Arm is the only Judge of Controverſies. when the Fiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Seaſon comes in they throng to the Sea Coaſts, and when that is over retire again into the <hi>Laplands.</hi> Fixt habitations they have none, but remove their Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings according to the Seaſons for Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; their Houſes are made only to ſecure them againſt the Injury of the Weather, and the aſſaults of wild Beaſts; and for that purpoſe they firſt erect Four Poſts in the Figure of a Square, which they bind together with croſs Girders, and rear to them ſmaller pieces, faſtning all with Wythes; theſe except the door places, the poorer ſort wholly cover with boughs of Trees or ſuch like ſtuff, the richer with a courſe ſort of Woollen Cloth, or an ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſort of Canvas. Two doors have they in theſe Houſes, the fore door, which is of common uſe and entrance for the whole Family, and the back door, thro which the Men paſs, and that only when they go a Hunting, Fiſhing, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but all Women are forbid it, either becauſe that Sex is thought to be very inauſpicious to thoſe Exerciſes,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:151645:60"/>for if any (when he is a going a Hunting or the like,) do but meet a Woman, he preſently returns back and leaves his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign for that day; or becauſe the Image of their God <hi>Thor</hi> was commonly placed near their back door, from whoſe Sacrifices and Preſence all Women are wholly exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Theſe Houſes are diſtinguiſhed into ſeveral Partitions, not by any Wall, but only by great Poſts or Loggs of Wood laid upon the Ground; their Fire place is in the middle, about which the whole Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily lies, either upon the bare Earth or upon the Skins of Rein Deer, Bears, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> When they have a mind to change their Habitation, which they do conſtantly twice a Year, they unty this their Tent, take it away with them, and pitch it in a more convenient place. Another Sort of Houſes among them, are their Granaries and Store Houſes; which that they may the better ſecure their Proviſion from wild beaſts and vermin, they do not build upon the Ground, but at ſome diſtance from it, upon the bole or ſtump of a large Tree.</p>
               <p>The Ordinary Diet of the <hi>Laplanders,</hi> is either of Fiſh or the Fleſh of their Rein Deer, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Which they eat ſometimes raw, ſometimes boil'd, but for the moſt part dried in the air. Bread and Salt are
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:151645:60"/>unknown to them, inſtead of Bread they make uſe of their dry'd Fiſh, groun'd ſmall like Meal: And for Salt they take the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of the Pine Trees, which they dry in the Sun, and putting it into Boxes bury it a ſmall depth in the Ground, then after it hath lain there a competent time, they kindle a fire upon the place and ſo dry it; whereby it becomes of a rediſh co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, a pleaſant taſte, and gives a good guſt and reliſh to their courſer Food.</p>
               <p>Their general Drink is pure Water, which in the Winter time they keep in their Houſes continually hot, and ſo drink it. Of late they are grown ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with Brandy and Liquors of that nature, which are in great vogue with them, and which they drink only on their Holy Days and at their Weddings. Their Dining Room is commonly in the middle of their Tent about the Fire, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Tables, Diſhes, Spoons or Trenchers, and ſuch ſort of Implements; each lays his Commons upon his Mittens, and when he has eat it, ſays Grace, ſhakes his Camrades by the right Hand, which is their Charity Cup; and ſo every one trudges about his buſineſs.</p>
               <p>Their Garments are very courſe and mean, made either of the Skins of Wild Beaſts, (frequently in uſe amongſt them)
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:151645:61"/>or the worſt of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Cloth, which they wear only on Holy Days and at their Publick Fairs. They alter them accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Seaſon of the Year; and each Sute for diſtinction ſake, has a ſeveral Mode and Faſhion: The Men uſe a Long Garment reaching down from their Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle to their Ankles, which ſerves them for Breeches and Stockings; above this they have a ſort of Wollen Coat call'd Mudd, which they tye about them with a Leathern Thong. Their Shoes, as the the reſt of their ordinary Garments, are made of the ſhins of rein Deer, Elks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with the hair outward, the toe bending ſomewhat upward, and according to the ancient Cuſtom, ending with a ſharp point: On their Heads they have a Cap made of the Skin of ſome Fowl, as Geeſe, Ducks, or the like, but particularly make choice of the Loom for that purpoſe, and like the ancient <hi>Germans</hi> taking the Feathers, Head and Wings along vvith it. The Garb proper to Women is a large vvide Govvn, made either of Cloth or Skins, according to the Perſons Condition and Eſtate: this Govvn is gathered cloſe in the middle, and decked vvith ſeveral Figures of Birds, Beaſts, and the like, vvhich they vvork very prettily and vvith great art.</p>
               <p>As for their Religion, before the plant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:151645:61"/>of Chriſtianity in that Countrey, which nevertheleſs has made but little progreſs among 'em, and would be entirely aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, were it not for the ſtrictneſs of the Government; they had their Deities pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick and common to the whole Nation, and others belonging onely to a Family, a Diviſion, a Neighbourhood; their greater Gods were the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Fire,</hi> their leſſer was <hi>Wira Accha,</hi> repreſented by an old ſtump of a Tree: they alſo pay Adoration to the Ghoſts of Men depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, eſpecially of their Relations and Friends, whom they conſider as Divinities; they worſhip alſo <hi>Spectres</hi> and <hi>Demons,</hi> which they fancy wander among the Rocks, Woods, Rivers and Lakes; they do the like to their <hi>Genius</hi>'s good or bad, whom they ſay fly in the air about <hi>Chriſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Their Gods common to the whole Countrey be <hi>Thor</hi> or <hi>Thiermes,</hi> that is, <hi>Thunderer</hi> or <hi>Noiſe-maker,</hi> they honour him with endearing and lofty Titles, as, <hi>Great-Grand-Father</hi> and the like; they fancy his abode to be in the Clouds, and that he diſpoſes of Wind, Rain, Thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, good and bad Weather, as he thinks fitting: He it is they think gives Life or Death, Health or Sickneſs, Bleſſings or Sufferings: They make his Image of
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:151645:62"/>Beech-Tree, eaſily turning the ſtoops which ſhoot out from the root into the likeneſs of a Mans Head, Arms, Feet, and the reſt, laying by him a Bow, Arrows, and a Hammer to kill the miſchievous <hi>Demons.</hi> They place their Images upon a Table in a piece of Ground dedicated to that Service, not far from their Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the Table ſerves them for an Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, and the Boughs of Birch and Pine for a Temple. They ſuffer not their Women to be preſent at the Sacrifices they offer to him, looking upon that as very Criminal. But they never offer Sacrifice till they have enquired of their God whether he will accept it or no: And this they do with a certain Inſtrument which they call <hi>Kannees,</hi> reſembling much the old faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Drums, on which they picture ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of their Gods: The whole manner of the Ceremony being as followeth, They pull off ſome of the hair at the bottom of the Beaſts Neck which is to be ſacrificed, and bind it to a Ring which is faſtned to the Drum, then one of them beats the Drum, and all the reſt ſing theſe words, <hi>What ſayeſt thou, O great and ſacred god, doth thou accept this Sacrifice whic we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to offer unto thee?</hi> And while ſome Chant theſe Words, others repeat the Name of the Mountain where they are;
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:151645:62"/>then if the Ring reſts on that part of the Drum where the God is pictured, they take it for granted the God is pleaſed; and ſo proceed to the Ceremony; or elſe cary the Sacrifice to <hi>Storejunkar</hi> or ſome other God, uſing the like Form of words, <hi>Father god will you have my ſacrifice?</hi> Their uſual Sacrifices are Rein-Deers, Cats, Lambs and Hens. The uſual time of their offering up their Sacrifices is in <hi>Autumn,</hi> becauſe that Winter and Nights approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they think they have the more need of their Gods aſſiſtance: Their way of Conſecrating is in this manner, Firſt they Sacrifice the Rein-Deer, then taking out his Bones they anoint the Idol with the Blood and Fat, and bury the Fleſh and Bones under ground, but this they do not till the God has approved of the Sacrifice, after which they bind the Rein-Deer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the houſe, then with a ſharp knife they run him thro the heart, and gather the heart blood, wherewith they anoint the I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dol, into a Veſſel. After that having placed the Images right, making a new one eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry time they ſacrifice, and ſetting them in order behind one another, the laſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways hindmoſt, they approach with reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to it, anoint the Head and Back all over with the blood, but on his Breaſt they only draw ſeveral croſſes, behind him
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:151645:63"/>they place the Skull, Feet and Horns of the ſacrificed Deer; before him they place a Coffer made of the bark of Birch, into whic they put a bit of every Member of the <hi>Rein Deer,</hi> withſome of the <hi>Fat;</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Fleſh</hi> they convert to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate uſes.</p>
               <p>The next of their Principal <hi>Gods</hi> is <hi>Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junkar,</hi> that is, <hi>Great Commander,</hi> he they ſay preſides peculiarly over all Beaſts and Cattle; this Gods Name they reverence with the higheſt reſpect, and pay him fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenter, if not greater Devotion than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods, for they ſuppoſe him to be their <hi>Thor</hi> or <hi>Thiermes</hi> Lieutenant, and worſhip him becauſe that they think they receive all their <hi>Bleſſings</hi> thro his <hi>hands,</hi> and that all <hi>Beaſts</hi> and <hi>Cattle</hi> are ſubject to his <hi>Will,</hi> and he governs <hi>them</hi> as <hi>Thiermes</hi> does <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Spirits;</hi> wherefore he can give them to whom he will, and none can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them without his pleaſure: Thus, <hi>Thiermes</hi> and <hi>Storejunkar</hi> are the two pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar <hi>Gods</hi> of the <hi>Laplanders,</hi> the one hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Dominion</hi> over the <hi>Men,</hi> the other over <hi>Beaſts;</hi> one beſtows life, the other all things neceſſary for the ſuſtenance of it. When they offer <hi>Sacrifice</hi> to <hi>Storejunkar,</hi> which is likewiſe a <hi>Male Deer,</hi> they firſtrun a <hi>Red Thred</hi> thro his <hi>Right Ear,</hi> and bind <hi>Him,</hi> and ſacrifice <hi>Him</hi> in the place where
<pb n="611" facs="tcp:151645:63"/>they did the like to <hi>Thor, preſerving</hi> the <hi>blood</hi> alſo in a Veſſel; then he who performs the Ceremony takes the <hi>Horns</hi> and the <hi>Bones</hi> of the <hi>Head</hi> and <hi>Neck,</hi> with the <hi>Feet</hi> and <hi>Hoofes,</hi> and caries them to the <hi>Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain</hi> of that <hi>Storejunkar,</hi> for whom the <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice</hi> was deſigned: When he comes near the <hi>ſacred ſtone</hi> he reverently uncovers his head and bowes his body, paying all the Ceremonies of Reſpect and Honour, then he anoints the <hi>Stone</hi> with the <hi>Fat</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> and places the <hi>Horns</hi> behind it; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the right <hi>Horn</hi> they faſten the <hi>Rein-Deers Yard,</hi> and to the left ſome red <hi>Thred</hi> wrought upon <hi>Tin</hi> with a little piece of <hi>Silver.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third and laſt of their Principal Gods is the <hi>Sun,</hi> whom they call <hi>Baiw,</hi> and worſhip him chiefly for his Light and Heat; alſo becauſe they believe him to be the Author of Generation, and that all things are made by his means, eſpecially their <hi>Rein-Deers,</hi> of whom and their Young, they think he hath a peculiar care to cheriſh by his Heat, and bring ſuddenly to Strength and Maturity. And being they live in a cold Country, where their heat is diminiſhed and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten wholly extinguiſh'd, being they have nothing to ſuſtain themſelves with but the fleſh of <hi>Rein Deer;</hi> they think it very fit to pay the <hi>Sun</hi> very great Honours; who is the Author of ſo great Bleſſings to them, and who at his return reſtores them that Light which they loſt by his departure, and that not for a day or two, but for ſeveral Weeks, which being paid, the new days ſeems
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:151645:64"/>welcome to them, by reaſon of long abſence. Now the Sacrifices they uſe to the <hi>Sun</hi> are young <hi>Rein Deers,</hi> and thoſe not <hi>Bucks,</hi> but <hi>Does,</hi> the <hi>Rites</hi> being much the ſame with thoſe before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, except only inſtead of a red String thro' the right Ear of <hi>Storejunkars Sacrifice,</hi> they run a white one thro the <hi>Suns;</hi> then they make a Garland, not of <hi>Birch</hi> but <hi>Willow,</hi> about as big as the Hoop of an Hogſhead. This they place upon a Table be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind the Hut, where they Sacrifice to <hi>Thor;</hi> not upon the ſame Table, but one like it. And this Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice differs from the <hi>Other,</hi> in that there are neither Images erected here, nor Horns, the <hi>Beaſts</hi> not being come to their growth. But that there may be ſome risſemblance of the Sun, they place their chief Bones of the Sacrifice upon the Table in a Circle.</p>
               <p>But the <hi>Laplanders</hi> are not more nototorious for their Idolatry than for their Witchcraft; anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and modern Writers aſſerting that they have attained to ſo great a skill in Enchantments and Magick, as that among ſeveral other ſtrange Effects of their Art, they could ſtop Ships when under full Sail, nay and could either by their looks, words, or ſome other wicked Artifice, to enſnare and bewitch Men, as to deprive them of the uſe of Limbs and Reaſon, and very often bring them into extream peril of their lives. Now one of the main Reaſons and Motives of their ſo doing, is, that every one thinks it the ſafeſt way to defend himſelf from the injurious and malicious deſigns of others; for they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly profeſs that their knowledg in theſe things is abſolutley neceſſary, for their own ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity. Wherefore they have Teachers, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:151645:64"/>in this Science; and Parents in their laſt Will bequeath to their Children as the greate part of their Eſtate, thoſe Spirits and Devils that have been any ways ſerviceable to them in their life time. Now as to the bequeathing their Familiars to their Children, they conſider it as the only means to raiſe their Family, ſo that they excel one another in this Art, according to the largeneſs of the Legacies they receive. By which it is apparent that every Family hath peculiar Spirits, and of different and quite contrary Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures from thoſe of others; and as each houſe, ſo has each ſingle perſon his particular Spirits, ſometimes one, two or more; but there are a ſet number of obſequious Spirits, beyond which none hath. Nevertheleſs ſome of theſe Spirits will not engage themſelves without great Soli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citation and earneſt Entreaties, whereas others will readily offer themſelves to little Children, when they find them capacitated for their turn, ſo that ſeveral of the Inhabitants are almoſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally Magicians; for when the Devil takes a liking to any perſon in his Infancy, as a fit In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument for his purpoſes, he preſently ſeizes on him by a Diſeaſe, in which he haunts him with ſeveral Apparitions, from whence accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Capacity of his Years and Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, he knows what belongs to the Art. Thoſe who are thus taken a ſecond time ſee more Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and gain far greater knowledge. If they are ſeized a third time, which is ſeldom with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out great torment or utmoſt danger of their life, the Devil appears to them in all his ſhapes, by which they arrive to the very Perfection of his Art, and become ſo knowing, that without a
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:151645:65"/>Drum they can ſee things at greateſt Diſtances, and are ſo poſſeſſed by the Devil, that they ſee them even againſt their will. And a certain <hi>Swediſh</hi> Author tells a ſtrange Story of a <hi>Laplan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> who upon complaint made againſt him for keeping a Drum, brought it, and delivered it up to him, and with Tears confeſt, that tho he thus willingly parted with it, and never intended to provide another, yet he ſhould ſtill be tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the ſame fearful and troubleſome Viſions about future Events, which (tho' his Eyes were ſhut) were always preſent to his im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agination, giving him a true and particular Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of whatever had happened to him in his Journey to <hi>Lapland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for the Art it ſelf, it is according to the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity of Inſtruments uſed in it, divided into two parts, one comprehends all that to which the Drum belongs; the other, thoſe things to which Knots, Darts, Spells, Conjurations, and the like refer: The Drum is peculiar to the <hi>Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers,</hi> and called by them <hi>Kannus</hi> or <hi>Quochdas,</hi> made of a hollow piece of Wood, and muſt be either of Pine, Fir, or Birch Tree, which grows to ſuch a particular place, and turns directly according to the Suns Courſe; which is when the Grain of the Wood running from the bottom to the top of the Tree; winds it ſelf from the right hand to the left. It is made hollow on one ſide, upon which they ſtretch a Skin, faſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it with wooden Pegs; on the other they make two holes to hold it by; the ſhape of the upper part is Oval, about half an Ell in Diameter; upon the Skin they paint ſeveral Pictures in red, ſtain'd with the Bark of an Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree; and through the middle they draw
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:151645:65"/>ſome croſs Lines in every Quarter, of which they place their Attendants; neither do they alwaies obſerve the ſame Gods, and the ſame Methods. But this is obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable, that they commonly paint the Sun in the middle, their Gods above, and the earthly things under him. And ſince Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity was introduced among them, many of them do place upon their Drum the Image of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his Apoſtles, owning him to be, or to have the power of one of their Gods. Moreover, they alter their figures according to the occaſion of the inquiry, retaining the general Notions the Heathens had of their Deity, that ſeveral of them had peculiar Offices and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. But now, though in many places they have been forced to abandon their Drums, yet do they practice all their knots, have their familiars in the ſhape of Flies, Bees, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But chiefly their black Cats (whom they not only Conſult at home about their Domeſtick affairs, but take with them alſo in their huntings; tho in the depths of Snow;) and their Diaboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Exerciſes, which are performed ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times with, ſometimes without a Drum: If with a Drum, the Sorcerer kreels down, and having a bunch of Rings, and other pieces of Braſs laid in the middle of
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:151645:66"/>the Drum, he beats with a Conſecrated Hammer, ſo ſtrongly, that the Rings dance upon it, by the reſting of which upon ſuch a figure, they draw forth an anſwer to what they would deſire to know; but if this be not ſatisfactory, then the Drummer puts himſelf by dancing and howling into a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent motion, till he falls down, which he chuſes to do upon his Drum; and then he lies without motion and diſturbance, and without ſenſe, till he voluntarily riſe again, and gives anſwer to what is deſired. This kind of Divination is chiefly uſed, when ſomething at a great diſtance is deſired to be known. The Stories are ſo frequent, and from perſons not over credulous, that there is no room left to doubt of what they ſay concerning theſe Sorceries. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other Inſtances thereof, this is rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by a Perſon of worth and underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; who being one time at Dinner with his Father, Mother, Brother, Siſter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> his Fathers knife was miſſing upon the ſudden, and could not be found, till two years after a Counſin of his returning from being Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor in, or near <hi>Lapland,</hi> brought it with him, telling them, that out of curioſity he had employed a <hi>Laplander,</hi> a pretender to great skill in this Art, to bring him notice of the health and condition of that Family;
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:151645:66"/>who after he had lain ſometime in this now deſcribed manner, brought him news, that they were all well, that he found them at Dinner; and that to confirm his Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, he brought away that knife, which he delivered to the Merchant, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant brought home now to his Uncle.</p>
               <p>As I ſaid before, they ſometimes pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice theſe Sorceries without the Drum, uſing inſtead of it commonly Strings or Darts, by which they advantage their friends, or injure their enemies at their pleaſure. The ſtrings they make uſe of to raiſe or quell the Winds, which they ſell to Mariners for that purpoſe. They con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt commonly of three knots; the firſt of which being untied, affords a favourable Wind; the ſecond a brisk Gale; and the third a violent Storm; as has been approved to the great peril &amp; loſs of ſeveral Seafaring perſons, that have given account of it in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick. By their Darts, which are ſhort Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of Lead; they wound any one who hath done them an injury, or their malice puts them upon to aſſault: Theſe are ſaid to be the moſt powerful Charms of any, &amp; upon occaſion to have ſplit Rocks, level'd Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains, and ſuch like incredible Exploits.</p>
               <p>They have Matrimony in great venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, it being ſeldom known they commit
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:151645:67"/>Adultery, but if ſuch a crime be once diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, it is ſeverely puniſhed. Now, when ever any man purpoſes to marry, his firſt buſineſs is, to make inquiry after a Maid well ſtock'd with <hi>Rain-Deers;</hi> for the <hi>Lap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landers</hi> have a Cuſtom of beſtowing upon their Children ſoon after their Birth, ſome certain number of thoſe <hi>Rain Deers,</hi> and their Encreaſe is accounted of not as the Parents Eſtate, but the Child's Portion. Thus ſhe, who has the greateſt number of them, is in the faireſt way to have a Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band. Nor have they regard to any thing elſe, not minding either good Breed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or Beauty, or other the common al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lurements of Wooers. Now the Spark ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving pitched upon a Miſtreſs, informs one of his neareſt friends of his Intentions, and deſires him to be his Spokes-man: This Kinſman of his ſollicits the buſineſs with her Father, Mother, and Kindred, preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and cajoling them with Brandy and Tobacco, or what elſe is moſt in requeſt in order to the purchaſing their Conſent. After this the Suitor has an Invitation to the Hut where the Bride dwells, where he agrees to certain Articles offered by her friends, and then liſts himſelf for a whole year in her Fathers ſervice; though firſt
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:151645:67"/>preſenting the Father with a Silver Cup, &amp; Kettle of either Copper or Alchimy, and a Bed, or at leaſt handſom Bedding. To the Mother he gives a Girdle of Silver, a Robe of Honour, and a Whisk, which they wear about their neck, and let it hang down to their breaſt, interlaced all about with Boſſes of Silver. Beſides, he beſtows upon the Brothers and Siſters, and all the Kindred, Silver Spoons, Silver Boſſes, and ſome other ſuch knick knacks of Silver; for each of them muſt be preſented with ſome gifts by the Bridegroom, if he mean to obtain his Bride. But the time of his years Service being expired, he takes to him his Wife, and proceeds to the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing the Marriage, which is ever per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed with great Pomp and Ceremony, according to their abilities. The Bride is ſpruc'd up with the Choiceſt Ornaments they can get, as pieces of Tin and Alchi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, with ſeveral Rings of Fiſh Bones and Braſs; though a Bride of the Richer ſort firſt looſes her hair, and the Fillet where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with ſhe bound it up together before, ſhe gives to the Virgin that is next akin to her: Afterwards on her bare head and looſe hair ſhe puts a kind of Silver Fillet, guilt over, or two, ſuch as is the womens Cuſtom to wear at other times, inſtead
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:151645:68"/>of a Garland or Coronet, which is practiſed in <hi>Denmark, Sweden,</hi> and other Northern Countrys, ſo that by how much this Fillet is looſer then to environ only her head; ſo much it hangs down the more behind. Like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe about the middle they put on a Silver Girdle, the Bridegroom too is as ſpruice as poſſible he can be, having the beſt cloaths on he can get at his own charges, and thoſe girded with a Silver Girdle. Thus adorn'd is the Bride dragg'd to Church, or to the Prieſt, ſeeming to go with much reluctance, and there is married according to the uſual Forms. In former times Matrimony was ſolemnized by the Parents and Friends (the Father ſupplying the place of the Prieſt, by ſtriking of Flint and Steel, the pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>teſt Emblem, as they thought, of a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried life; for as the Flint conceals within it Fire, which by concuſſion breaks forth; ſo in both Sexes there is life hid, which by the mutual coupling of Marriage, is propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated at laſt to be a living Off-ſpring. Poligamy is not allowed of among them, a man being ſuffered to have but one Wife at a time. Nor do they contract Wed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lock without the conſent of their friends, to whom they refer themſelves wholly as to that matter. Thus a ſtoln Wedding is never heard of among them, neither
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:151645:68"/>are they ſuffered to trade for themſelves, until they have ſerved as Bondſmen their Father-in-law for a certain time, which Cuſtom does ſeem to be derived from the moſt Primitive Times and Nations.</p>
               <p>Peſtilential Diſtempers are very rarely known in this Country, the pureneſs of the Air ſtill correcting the malignity of them, when they happen to be introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. Pluriſies, Inflammations, and Soreneſs of the Eyes, they are ſometimes troubled with, which laſt they cure by drinking a Decoction of the Root of <hi>Moſs,</hi> or the Stalk of <hi>Angelica,</hi> in the Whey of the Milk of their <hi>Rain-Deer.</hi> They cure wounds with no other Ointments or Plaiſter than that of Roſin, which the Trees ſweat out: If a Member be benummed with cold, the the Cheeſe made of <hi>Rain-Deers</hi> Milk, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fords the preſenteſt Remedy to it; they thruſt a red hot Iron into it, and with the Fat of the Cheeſe that inſtantly diſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> from it, they anoint the part affected, with incredible ſucceſs; and when troubled with any Pains or Aches in their Joynts, or Body, as the Gout; Cramp, Sciatica, or the like, they eaſe and cure them by ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying a Cauſtick of the flame of any Chips to the affected place. Diſeaſes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus rare among them, and the Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:151645:69"/>ſo eaſie, they live to an extream old Age: many being known to live to above a hundred years old, and moſt uſually at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to Seventy, Eighty, and Ninety years, &amp; at this Age are ſtill ſufficiently brisk and lively, able to manage their buſineſs with expedition, to take a Journey, to Courſe through Woods and Mountains, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form other ſuch toil and labour, with great vigour; ſeldom do they grow grey, and that not till the very laſt declenſion of their Age; and it is found, that more of them are diſpatched by old Age, than Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſes.</p>
               <p>But when they perceive any one near Death, they ſend either for the Prieſt, if near at hand, to prepare him for his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, or elſe for a Magician, who is ſaid to be able to reſolve them by his Drums, of the very hour and manner of any mans Death. In caſe he dies, they fancy his Soul is reſtleſs till his Body be buried, which for that reaſon they do with all poſſible haſt, commonly carrying him to the neareſt Wood or Cave which they pitch upon for a burying-place, ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom interring them in Church-yards, by reaſon of their remoteneſs. The dead Corps they carry upon a Sledge, the perſon who conducts being particularly intreated
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:151645:69"/>to undertake the Employment, and muſt receive of the neareſt kinſman of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Perſon a Ring of <hi>Alchimy,</hi> and wear it faſtened to his Right Arm; the reaſon of which is, becauſe they believe it a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative againſt the miſchief the <hi>Manes</hi> of the Deceaſed Perſon may bring upon them and therefore is fain to wear this ſame Ring till the Burial be over. When they come with the Body to the Cave, they caſt it in, and the Sledge after it, or elſe cover it with great Logs of Wood, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it from wild Beaſts, never failing to lay by it a Hatchet, a Flint and Steel, that if ever they come to riſe again in the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, they ſhall have great need of ſpring<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing a light; to which the Flint &amp; Steel may help them; as likewiſe there will be occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion for a ready way wherein they may travel to Heaven, to which purpoſe their Hatchet may ſtand them inſtead, them eſpecially that are buried in thick Woods, that if any Trees obſtruct their paſſage, they may cut them down. When they come home from the burial, they make ready a Funeral-banquet, or rather indeed a Sacrifice to the Ghoſt of the Deceaſed Perſon, which they perform, by taking thoſe <hi>Rain-Deer,</hi> who drew the Corps to the Grave, and offer them in Sacrifice to
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:151645:70"/>the <hi>Manes,</hi> revelling upon the fleſh with Brandy and Tobacco, and quaffing round a Health to the Deceaſed Perſon, calling the Brandy which they uſe for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the <hi>Wine of the Bleſſed,</hi> meaning that they drink it to the memory of him, that is happy by his departure from Earth. At this Feaſt they take ſpecial care not to loſe the Bones of the ſacrificed <hi>Rain-Deer,</hi> but gather them all up diligently, and lay them in a Coffer, and bury them under ground; but firſt faſten upon the Coffer wherein they ſhut up the <hi>Rain-Deers</hi> Bones, the Image of a Man faſhioned out of Wood, bigger or leſs in proportion to the Deceaſed Perſon.</p>
               <p>But the Scepter of <hi>Denmark</hi> extending over but a ſmall part of <hi>Lapland,</hi> it is not neceſſary to inlarge upon the other To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picks, which the Deſcription of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try does afford; wherefore we will leave it, and ſteer our Courſe towards.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>The Iſlands of <hi>Fero.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE Iſlands of <hi>Fero</hi> are only many high Rocks and Mountains covered with thin Earth, of about two foot deep, and divided from each other by rapid ſtreams of deep water: Part of them are inhabited, and part ſtocked with Cattle;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:151645:70"/>the Account whereof, with their Havens, Creeks, Inlets, and other Circumſtances, take as followeth.</p>
               <p>They are Seventeen in number; <hi>Fugloe,</hi> or <hi>Fowle-Iſland,</hi> about two <hi>Engliſh</hi> Miles in breadth, and three in length. 2. <hi>Swino,</hi> in which is a pleaſant Valley of a mile is length. 3. <hi>Vederoe,</hi> ſix Miles long, and three broad. 4. <hi>Bordoe,</hi> ſix Miles in length 5. <hi>Kunoe</hi> is a long and narrow Iſland, much of the ſame bigneſs as <hi>Bordoe.</hi> 6. <hi>Kalſoe</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſeven Miles long, &amp; near two Miles broad, 7. <hi>Oſteroe</hi> is almoſt twenty Miles in length, but unequal in breadth; for ſome places are two miles broad, others four or ſix Miles broad, according as the points ſtretch themſelves far out. 8. <hi>Fromoe</hi> twenty four Miles long, and eight broad, being the largeſt of the <hi>Feroe</hi> Iſlands, and contains the Town of <hi>Thorſhaven,</hi> the <hi>Metropolis</hi> and place of greateſt Trade of them all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 9. <hi>Wagoe,</hi> a round piece of ground of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout eight miles in Diameter. 19. <hi>Mig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geneſs,</hi> three miles long, and one and a had broad, having a high Territory, with high Promontories round about it, there being but one place to come on Land. 11. <hi>Kol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> a ſmall Iſland, a Mile in length, and half a Mile in breadth. Betwixt twenty and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty years ago, there was found on the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:151645:71"/>higheſt top of the Mountain of <hi>Kolter,</hi> the quantity of many Tonnes of Herrings ſpread along; the Mountain where the Herrings were found is above two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred fathoms high, being carried thither by a Whirl-wind. 12. <hi>Sandoe</hi> eight Miles long, and four Miles broad. 13. <hi>Skuo</hi> three Miles long, and one broad. 14. <hi>Forcdie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> or <hi>Great Dam,</hi> is almoſt round, being a good Mile in Diameter, with a high Territory, for the moſt part flat and green, above with great Clefis round about. 13. <hi>Lille-Diemen,</hi> a ſmall Iſland, whereon feed a vaſt number of wild Sheep<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16. <hi>Suderoi,</hi> twenty Miles long, and eight broad, having a very good little harbour <hi>fiord,</hi> having a bowed Creek, where there is one of the beſt. Havens in <hi>Fero,</hi> called called <hi>Punthaven.</hi> And laſtly, 17. <hi>Vaageſ-Lebroc.</hi> Beſides, four little Iſles, or <hi>Holmes,</hi> namely, <hi>Tintholm, Muggeneſholm, Troleho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred,</hi> and <hi>Lilly-Diemen,</hi> which afford only Paſture for wild Sheep, with ſeveral other ſmaller Holms, whereof the moſt neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary to be known by Mariners are <hi>Hof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frigſholm, Kirckbockholm,</hi> and <hi>Combocholm.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Air of theſe Iſlands is temperate in all ſeaſons, not over-hot in Summer, nor ſo violent cold in Winter, as to cauſe Ice in any of the Bays, and withal wholſom, and
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:151645:71"/>free from all Contagious Diſeaſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> unleſs introduced by Strangers; ſo that the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants generally attain to a very long life: Yet the Scurvey, the Leproſie, and a ſort of Feveriſh Diſtemper, by the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants called <hi>Landſarforo,</hi> are Epidemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Diſeaſes, which reign in moſt of theſe Iſlands, but rarely prove mortal. Beſides, the Inhabitants are exceedingly ſubject to Rheums, which occaſion Coughs and Head-achs, which they nevertheleſs cure by drinking ſome Whey, as hot as they can bear it. Thunder they never hear in Summer, but often in Winter, Spring and Autumn, and that too attended with vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Storms.</p>
               <p>The Fertility of theſe Iſlands is not over great, they affording hardly any other grain than Barley, whereof, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs a Tun of Seed will commonly yield twenty or thirty Tun of grain. But their Paſture-grounds abound in good and ſweet Graſs, and thoſe ſtockt with as large and fat Oxen, as ſhall be ſeen in any other part of <hi>Europe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe Iſlands do likewiſe abound in all ſorts of Medicinal herbs, as Scurvey-graſs, Water-creſſes, Sorrel, <hi>angelica;</hi> as alſo <hi>Radix Rhodia,</hi> which is no where met with in ſuch abundance, as upon the
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:151645:72"/>Banks of Running Streams and Lakes in theſe Iſlands. Thus they want nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſie for the cure of ſuch Diſtempers as the Natives are moſt ſubject to.</p>
               <p>Great plenty, and variety of Fowl is here to be found, as doves, Stares, Owls, Sparrow-Hawks, Crows, Grillins, and Ravens, as well white, as others. The Sea-Fowl with them in moſt requeſt is a kind of Teal, about the bigneſs of a Crow, with a long, round, and yellow Bill. The Eyder (a ſort of Duck, which yields the Eyder Down) is a Bird pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to theſe Iſlands, and which uſually pulls the Down from her own Breaſt to make her Neſt withal. When her young one are fledg'd and fled, the Natives take away the Down, and change it for uſe. But if the Feathers be pull'd off by man, they rot away forthwith, and are of no uſe. Another remarkable Fowl they have by them, called <hi>Imbrim,</hi> with a long Neck and Beak, the Back grey, and chequer'd with white ſpots, with a white Ring about the Neck: This Bird has two holes under her Wings, each large enough to hold an Egg; here 'tis thought ſhe hatches two Eggs at once, being never ſeen with above two young ones at a time, nor known to come aſhore.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:151645:72"/>
The neighbouring Seas do provide the Natives with God, Whiting, large Floun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Marts a kind of Pilchards, of which ſuch ſtore, that the Havens and Creeks are filled with them, beſides, Seals, Grind Whales, Morſſes, and Dogfiſh, though their fiſhing Trade is much decayed of late years to what it was formerly.</p>
               <p>Theſe Iſlands were firſt inhabited by <hi>Norwegians</hi> about the year 840. and ſo the <hi>Norwegian</hi> tongue was for a long while generally ſpoke, though of late years the <hi>Daniſh</hi> Dialect has much prevailed.</p>
               <p>The people are humble and civil to one another, and eſpecially Courteous to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; Loyal, and liberal in their Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to the Government, and Charitable to the Poor: they are moderate and fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal in their Dyet, which is chiefly on Milk, Fiſh, Gruel, and Fleſh. They dry both their Fleſh and Fiſh in the Wind, having Wind houſes for that purpoſe, when the fleſh is dryed, they boyl it in Water, and thicken the Broth with Barley Meal; which is reckon'd one of their greateſt Delicacies.</p>
               <p>As for their Apparel, the Men wear woollen ſhirts, flannel Trowces, and Waſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coats, with ſhort looſe Coats of the ſame. The Women rich and poor, go all alike, in ſtrait Growns without skirts. Their
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:151645:73"/>Stomachers are commonly large, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorn'd with thin gingling guilt plates of Tin. Their Shoes have no ſoles, but have pieces of leather drawn together at the Heels and Toes, and faſtned with a ſtring, or ribband about the Ancle, and are of Sheep-skin for the Women, and tann'd Neats leather for the Men. They lie on Beds of Hay, overſpread with pieces of flannel.</p>
               <p>Theſe People were firſt Converted to Chriſtianity in the year 1000. by <hi>Sigiſmoad Briſtyon,</hi> a Native of <hi>Fero,</hi> who was ſent by the King of <hi>Denmark</hi> into his own Country for that purpoſe, Immediately after the <hi>Augsbourg</hi> Confeſſion was recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in <hi>Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Norway,</hi> it was eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in <hi>Fero,</hi> theſe Iſlands containing at this day thirty nine Pariſhes, which are all officiated by Miniſters of the Lutheran Religion. Beſides <hi>Sundays,</hi> Holy-days, and the uſual days of Prayer, as in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they annually obſerve ſix peculiar days of Prayer, three in <hi>Aſcenſion</hi> week, and three in <hi>Michaelmas</hi> week. They have one publick School endowed by King <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian</hi> the 4. and <hi>Nichilas Trolls,</hi> Vice-Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miral of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As to the Government of theſe Iſlands, it is divided into the ſix Diſtricts of <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deroe,
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:151645:73"/>Oſtaroe, Stromoe, Waaegoe, Sandoe,</hi> and <hi>Sanorce.</hi> Each of theſe Diſtricts has a Sheriff, who ſits as Judge, and determines all Cauſes and Controverſies of leſs mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The Laws of <hi>Norway</hi> are the <hi>Laws</hi> of theſe Iſlands. They having none pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar of their own.</p>
               <p>The Eccleſiaſtical affairs are governed by a Synod of the Prieſts and Miniſters, who meet and fit once a year. Out of the whole Synod one is Elected to preſide o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the reſt, with the title of Provoſt.</p>
               <p>The Principal Commodities theſe Iſlands afford, are Skins, Feathers, Tallow, Train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyl, and Stockings; upon all which there is a particular price ſet. Stockins are the chief ſtaple Commodity they have, in the making of which, all the Inhabitants of all Conditions are conſtrained to employ them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves for the getting a lively-hood, which the ſmallneſs of their Incomes, their ſlender poſſeſſions, and inconſiderable ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends, would hardly otherwiſe afford.</p>
               <p>As for the Iſle of <hi>Schetland,</hi> which many will have to be the Ancient <hi>Thule,</hi> it lies about ſixty Degrees, &amp; a few odd Minutes of Northern latitude, and has nothing very obſervable, the manners of its Inhabitants, the natuae of its Soyl, the temperature of its Air <hi>&amp;c.</hi> being much the ſame as in <hi>Iſeland.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <pb n="140" facs="tcp:151645:74"/>
               <head>Of Iſeland.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſeland</hi> is an Iſle in the <hi>Deucalidonian</hi> Seas, ſcituate under the <hi>Artick</hi> Circle, at 13 Degrees, and 30 min. of longitude, and 65 deg. and 44 min. of latitude; being bounded on the Eaſt with the <hi>Northern</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean; on the <hi>South</hi> with the <hi>Deucaledonian</hi> Sea; on the <hi>North</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> with the frozen Sea of <hi>Greeland.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Diſcovery of this Iſland was firſt made by one <hi>Naddoc;</hi> who ſayling near the Coaſts of the <hi>Fero</hi> Iſlands, was by a ſtorm forc'd upon the <hi>Northern</hi> parts of this Iſland, which by reaſon of the abundance of Snow, wherewith the Country was then covered, he called <hi>Sneeland.</hi> After that, it was a ſecond time diſcovered by a <hi>Sweediſh</hi> Marriner called <hi>Gardar,</hi> who called it <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>darſholm,</hi> after his own name, and finally diſcovered by one <hi>Flocco</hi> a <hi>Norwegian</hi> Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, who called it <hi>Iſeland,</hi> from the vaſt quantities of Ice in it, and about it; being frozen continually for the ſpace of eight months, and ſo vehemently chilled with the <hi>Northern</hi> winds, that it yieldeth neither Corn nor Trees, except Juniper only.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:151645:74"/>
                  <hi>Ingulph</hi> a <hi>Norwegian</hi> Baron, is ſaid to have brought the firſt Inhabitants into this Iſland, in the year 874. though there is reaſon to believe it was peopled before that time, &amp; known too, by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> it being acknowledged, that the Ancient <hi>Iſelan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> called the <hi>Iriſh Papey,</hi> and the <hi>Weſtern</hi> part of their Iſle, as moſt frequented by <hi>Iriſh</hi> Merchants <hi>Papey.</hi> Beſides, there is ſtill ſeveral remains and monuments of Idolatry in this Iſland, which ſhow its ancient Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants to have been Pagans, whereas the <hi>Danes</hi> and <hi>Norwegians</hi> at the time of their firſt ſetling there were Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>The modern Natives are for the moſt part plain and ſimple, living on what is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by nature, without the help of Art, more then that of making Cheeſe and Butter: the Mountains ſerving them for Towns, and the Rivers for Drink, and they quarter with their Horſes and their Oxen under one and the ſame roof. As they do not ſtand in need of either Phyſick or Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſician, ſo neither do they uſe any, their temperance in meat and drink, and the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally ſtrong conſtitution of their Bodies enabling many of them to attain to the age of 150 years, and more, Nay, <hi>Olaus Magnus</hi> affirms they commonly live to the age of three hundred years, and <hi>Blykenius</hi>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:151645:75"/>reports, that he ſaw a man in <hi>Iſeland,</hi> who told him that he had then lived two hund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red years.</p>
               <p>Their habitations are for the moſt part of timber, roofed with ſlags or turfs, with a hole on the ſide of the roof to let in their light; though in their Cities of <hi>Hola</hi> and <hi>Shalholt,</hi> inſtead of Tiles, they make uſe of fir-boards. But in their Hurts ſcatter'd up and down the Country, the <hi>Iſelanders</hi> and their Cattle have the ſame lodging for the poorer ſort of the Inhabitants, being deſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute of Wood and Turf, and not able to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe fuel from abroad, are forced in the extremity of Winter to betake themſelves to a corner of their Ox-ſtalls, and there borrow warmth from their Cattle.</p>
               <p>The food of the <hi>Iſelanders</hi> is upon Beef, Mutton, and the like, with moſt ſorts of Foul, which they have in great abundance, the truth is, they have no variety of Sau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but the ſharpneſs of the air furniſheth them with ſtomachs which need none. Fiſh they have great plenty of, and which dried, is indeed their only bread, and their Ling is ſo excellent, that even with us it is counted one of our greateſt Dainties.</p>
               <p>Their moſt common Drink is Whey, which is generally ſo good, that an ounce of it will very well bear half an Ounce of
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:151645:75"/>Water. They have alſo a ſort of Mead, made of Barley flower, and a Honey-comb boyled in Water, and another liquor ſquee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed out of a certain reddiſh Berry, pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar to this Iſle. But though they have neither Ale, Bear, nor Wine, they can make a ſhift to be ſumptuous, nay, profuſe in their Revels and Banquets, for we read that <hi>Theodore,</hi> and <hi>Thorwald</hi> (Brethren and Citizens of <hi>Hialtedat</hi> in <hi>North Iſeland</hi>) ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnizing the Funerals of their Father <hi>Hialta,</hi> entertained twelve hundred Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons for fourteen days together at a Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer; and at the departure of his Gueſts made 'em all preſents, every one ſuitable to his quality; many more inſtances have they of the ſame kind.</p>
               <p>They have little mony in <hi>Iſeland,</hi> what they have is <hi>Daniſh,</hi> but that in very ſmall quantity; bartering one Commodity for another, being their method of buying and ſelling, as it was of all other Nations in the Non-age of Commerce.</p>
               <p>The principal Commodities of this Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try are Whalebone, which they have in ſuch abundance, that many of 'em make Houſes of it, and the only Bridge in the Iſland is framed of the ſame matter, they alſo formerly exported vaſt quantities of Beef, Mutton, Butter and the like, and do
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:151645:76"/>ſtill, dryed Fiſh, and Brimſtone, the great Veins whereof do feed and nouriſh the flames of Mount <hi>Heela,</hi> which is one of the greateſt <hi>Vulcanoes</hi> in the Univerſe, it belches forth by fits ſuch inundations of fire, as menace the whole Iſle with a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral conflagration, vomiting not only flame &amp; fiery Coals, but large torrents of water, which burn like Brandy, or <hi>Aqua-vitae.</hi> At other times it caſts forth ſtupendious quantities of Cinders and pumice ſtones, inſomuch that it darkneth the Sun. The <hi>Weſt</hi> wind occaſions its greateſt outrages; ſo that when the wind blows moderately from that quarter, the People of the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Plains, knowing the ſafeſt paſſages to the Mountain, crow'd up to the mouth of the furnace, where they find their Diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion by throwing great ſtones into the flames, which return them with as great violence as a barrel of Gunpowder blows up the ſlates of a Houſe. Whereby a man runs great danger in approaching the flames who is not perfectly acquainted with eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the mountain, for he not only runs the riſque of being knocked on the head with ſome of thoſe ſtones which fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently comes to paſs, but alſo the ground does ſurprizingly open, and the flames ſwallow up men alive. Of this and two
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:151645:76"/>other Mountains in this Iſland called <hi>Helga</hi> and <hi>la Croix,</hi> more ſtrange circumſtances are related, than what are ſaid of <hi>Aetna,</hi> many of the ſilly ſuperſtitious Inhabitants believing that underneath it is Hell, and the abode of the damned, &amp; ſome do confidently report that they have frequently ſeen whole Herds of Devils throng into the mouth of the furnace with their Burthens of damn'd Souls, and having eas'd their ſhoulders, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn for a new leading. Nay, they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently pretend to know the very day that any Battle is fought in any part of the world, by obſerving the more than uſual importation of Souls on ſuch days. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place of Torments the Natives do i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magine to be under the Rocks on the Sea Coaſts, and the claſhing of the Ice againſt the ſhoar, and banks, makes ſuch a noiſe, as they take for the howling of the damn'd. There is alſo ſaid to be a Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain in <hi>Iſeland,</hi> which petrefies immediate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly whatever is thrown into it; ſo that if a man takes a long pole, and ſtick part of it into the bottom of the lake, that part of the ſtaff which ſticks in the Earth, will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently be turned into Iron, the middle into Stone, and the uppermoſt part remain Wood, which came not into the water, the ſame Authors write of another lake there
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:151645:77"/>which ſends forth ſuch peſtiferous exhala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as poyſon the Birds which flie that way.</p>
               <p>The modern language of <hi>Iſeland,</hi> is the true old <hi>Daniſh</hi> Tongue, uſed in ancient inſcriptions, and other monuments of <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> learning, which has been preſerved Chaſt and pure to this day in <hi>Iſeland,</hi> by reaſon of the little Commerce they have had with other Nations.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſeland</hi> was formerly divided into four Provinces, called <hi>Eaſt, Weſt, North,</hi> and <hi>South Iſeland,</hi> from the four quarters of the World: Each of theſe Provinces was ſubdivided into three leſſer Diſtricts, except North <hi>Iſeland,</hi> being larger, into four. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very Diſtrick had in it three publick Courts of Judicature, and ten or more <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>reppar,</hi> or Conſtable Wards, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Iſle was <hi>Ariſtocratical</hi> till the year 1260. when being brought under the Crown of <hi>Norway,</hi> it ſince followed the fortunes of it in all Changes of Church and State made ſubiect with it to the Kings of <hi>Denmark,</hi> together with it reformed in matters of Religion according to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion at <hi>Augsbourg,</hi> retaining ſtill their Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops with a limited power, and turning the Revenues of their eight Religious Houſes of <hi>Pingore, Remeſtede, Modur,</hi> and <hi>Monke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nire,</hi>
                  <pb n="147" facs="tcp:151645:77"/>under the Government and juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion of the Biſhop of <hi>Halar;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Videy, Pernebar, Kirckebar,</hi> and <hi>Skiade,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Biſhop of <hi>Schalholt</hi> unto other u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, according to the will and pleaſure of their Lords of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But their Gods in the time of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſm, were, 1. <hi>Thor,</hi> who is ſaid to have come out of <hi>Aſia,</hi> with his Father <hi>Woden,</hi> and is anſwerable to <hi>Jupiter</hi> among the <hi>Romans,</hi> and gave name to our <hi>Thurſday,</hi> in <hi>Iſeland</hi> called <hi>Thorſday,</hi> and by the <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans Donderdag,</hi> that is, <hi>the Thunderers day,</hi> which ſignifies the ſame thing. 2. <hi>Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> or <hi>Oden;</hi> the Captain of the <hi>Aſians,</hi> who firſt peopled theſe <hi>Northern</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys. From him the <hi>Iſelanders</hi> call the fourth day of the week <hi>Odens dagur,</hi> and we <hi>Wedneſday.</hi> Beſides theſe two, we ſometimes read of <hi>Freyer,</hi> one of <hi>Wodens</hi> Companions, and <hi>Friga, Wodens</hi> Spouſe (whence our <hi>Fryday</hi> with ſeveral others of leſs note.) They have but two Cities, and thoſe no better than our Ordinary Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, yet the Seats of their two Biſhops, the firſt is <hi>Hogin,</hi> the ſecond is <hi>Shalholt,</hi> their other places of any note are <hi>Hatten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort,</hi> a Haven Town, where under ten<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the <hi>Dutch</hi> Merchants barter their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities, and beſide a Caſtle, the ordinary
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:151645:78"/>Reſidence of the Governor for the Kings of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As for their Court of Judicature, it is held once a year in a pleaſant Plain in the middle of <hi>Iſeland,</hi> where twelve men lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Laws of <hi>Iſeland,</hi> having heard all the <hi>Plaintiffs</hi> and <hi>Defendants</hi> have to ſay, pronounce ſentence, and decide the Controverſies. And have power to deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine all Civil Cauſes, and pronounce Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation as they think convenient againſt all Criminals. Such as receive ſentence of Death, as Adulterers, Murderers, and Notorious Thieves, are beheaded; leſs Miſdemeanors and Offences are marked in the Fore-head with an hot Iron.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Freezland, <hi>or</hi> Friſeland.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FReezland</hi> ſo called from the continual froſts unto which it is ſubject, lies South-weſt of <hi>Iſeland</hi> in 60 degrees, more <hi>Weſterly</hi> than any part of <hi>Europe;</hi> it is ſaid to be little leſs in extent than <hi>England;</hi> being a ragged and high ſand, its mountains covered with Snow, and the Coaſt ſo full of drift Ice, that it is almoſt inacceſſible. The longeſt day in Summer not exceeding
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:151645:78"/>20 hours; nevertheleſs the Soil is ſo cold and barren, that it produceth neither Corn nor fruit, Fiſh being the principal, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt only Food of the Inhabitants, and as it is their Food, ſo it is the chief Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity the Country does afford, there being good fiſhing every where upon the Coaſt. It was firſt diſcovered to us by <hi>Nicolas</hi> and <hi>Antonio Zani,</hi> two <hi>Venetian</hi> Gentlemen that were here Shipwrackt. Our Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men in their ſoundings brought up a ſort of Pale Coral, and little ſtones clear as Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtal. They called it <hi>Weſt-England,</hi> and one of the higheſt Mountains <hi>Charing Croſs.</hi> The chief Town is called <hi>Friezland</hi> by the name of the Iſland; ſituate on the <hi>Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ern</hi> ſhore of it. Beſides we find ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in the Maps as <hi>Saneſtol, Ocebar, Caba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra, Sorand,</hi> and ſome more very inconſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. And now let us proceed on to <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="region">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of</hi> Greenland.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GReenland,</hi> ſo called, as ſome ſay, from the greenneſs of it in Summer, or as others, by <hi>Antiphraſis,</hi> for that it's never green, by reaſon of the ſharpneſs of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:151645:79"/>extends from 65. to 7 degrees of <hi>Northern</hi> latitude; ſo that the longeſt day in the moſt <hi>Southern</hi> parts is 21 hours and a half; and in the moſt <hi>Northern</hi> they have no night for three months and two weeks. The length of it is not known, nor whether it be an Iſland or a Continent, being chiefly frequented for the benefit of the Whale fiſhing. The chief commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities are Fiſh, white Bears, wild Deer, and ſome ſtore of Cattel there bred. The greateſt part of the people dwell in Caves, and delight to a high degree in Necroman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy Other Lands there be, but not of any note, nor hardly worth the Claiming of the Crown of <hi>Denmark.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:151645:79"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
